[Music]
hello welcome to convergent dialogues
this is xavier benia
okay on this episode i am very pleased
and honored to have
the extremely brilliant carl fristen
carl is a theoretical neuroscientist
and pretty much one of the major
authorities on brain imaging
he's a professor at the institute of
neurology at university college london
consultant for the national hospital for
neurology and neurosurgery in the united
kingdom
he
has invented many
aspects of brain imaging including the
statistical parametric mapping
voxel-based morphometry and dynamic
causal modeling
much of these were used in
schizophrenia research which we talked
about
he talks about this in terms of his
as his day job and then he has his
kind of weekend job
which is trying to
find these theoretical models and
structures of the human brain
um and one of these theoretical
neurobiological models is what he titles
the free energy principle which we talk
much about
which also has some connections with the
bayesian brain model
he is a fellow of the royal society of
biology
and he has many honorary doctorates and
we have a wide ranging conversation
about many many many topics this
conversation is over three hours
um and i was absolutely you know
privileged to
to get
three over three hours with with him he
was very generous with his time and his
his energy and his mind
and we we talk about everything we first
start by talking about the history of
models of the brain so over time
there have been many models of the brain
and so he gives a
history of what that looked like
we talk about the evolutionary
components of the brain and how
executive functioning and abstraction
work
with various organisms
we give an overview of the bayesian
brain talk about predictive coding and
or bayesian filtering
we talk about the two classes of neurons
for prediction error
and for predictions
he gives a very very nice
comprehensive explanation of the free
energy
principle
talk about the importance of a markov
blanket and
the importance of equilibrium and
homeostasis
we talk about the free energy principle
and a little bit of freudian
psychoanalysis and some of the
connection there
you talk about his views on
consciousness and how active inference
is in play
we talk about a.i
we talk about the various neuroimaging
techniques that i mentioned earlier
we talk about fmris and some of their
challenges there we also then end the
towards the
end of the conversation with how the
free energy principle could be used
pragmatically
um i have to say
this conversation is
um
it's long but it's it's very engaging
i found the conversation to be
very engaging and and even though it's
it's pretty dense in some in some areas
i've found it pretty easy to kind of
track and follow along so you know carl
does a really nice job of explaining
very
hard and difficult concepts
in
pretty easy to understand ways without
losing the integrity of of the concepts
and so
it definitely requires some attention
because these are some really
complicated
ideas
but i think it's super important um he's
doing really important work both in his
day job uh and in the imaging
for for the brain and then also his his
weekend java as he says for
trying to understand a theoretical
framework and to understand that the
neurophysiology and neurobiology of how
things work together
and how this can interact with
engineering
ai kind of computational neuroscience
neuropsychology etc so
again it was a an absolute uh honor and
privilege to to have him on the podcast
and he gave me so much time and energy
and so i'm very pleased to bring you
carl first him
i'm here with carl fristen
carl
it is a big honor and a privilege sir so
i thank you so much for coming on the
podcast and uh being willing to talk to
us about
your very important work and all the
things you've been researching so big
thanks to you
well it's a pleasure to be here thank
you for asking me of course
um so for folks that don't know who you
are kind of give your potted biography
just give us the snapshot of who you are
um what you do
uh what you study and all of the all the
particulars
right
i have my day job and my day job is a
professor of neuroscience at university
college london
um with a special expertise in
human brain scanning so
i originally trained as a psychiatrist
um and got into the field of imaging
neuroscience in an attempt to understand
disorders like schizophrenia by
literally looking at the brain
as best we could or as best we can using
modern technology
and then i have a weekend job which is
more of a theoretical neuroscientist
and laterally one could generalize that
to being a theoretical biologist or a
biomathematician trying to understand
the fundaments of
sentient behavior the principles that
underlie the way that we make sense of
the world
that
informs and is informed by the day job
so the more you know about how what the
brain must be doing uh the more you can
start to
look at the empirical results from the
brain imaging and understand the message
passing and the fluctuations and neural
activity in the service of sensemaking
yeah no this is very very important um i
i guess the i do want to ask you about
the imaging piece how did you kind of i
guess um
i guess stumble into this kind of way of
doing the day job and the weekend job
this is something that you mentioned you
were trained as a psychiatrist but was
this something that you always wanted to
do you were always curious about the
brain and looking at different ways of
understanding its functioning and then
did the theoretical stuff kind of come
later or how did this kind of i guess
morph into where you're at now uh and
what you're currently doing
that's an excellent question which i
could answer quickly or take a very long
time answering the question whichever
way you want
let's do the quick one i always wanted
to do this uh so what i am doing now is
really
the denouement of a series of uh
serendipitous of lucky career choices
that actually started around the
age of 15 wanting to be what in those
days would have been known as a
mathematical psychologist so
a dual commitment to
understanding the most interesting thing
which of course was me and my brain at
that time and other people's brain
but using a formal calculus uh your
principle approach so
trying to maintain a
training and investment in physics and
mathematics a sort of dual early career
in psychology and physics
and then
went into psychiatry
as the most alluring and i have to
confess the easiest way to become a
medic
at that point in time because everybody
else wanted to be a heart surgeon at
that time
it happens
everybody wants to be a gp nowadays but
my cohort they all wanted to be heart
surgeons um so but i ended up in
psychiatry and and very much valued that
experience but of course it was exactly
in the direction of travel um
in terms of what i ultimately wanted to
do which was research into
what would nowadays i guess be thought
of as um
theoretical neurobiology or
computational neuroscience but
essentially the formal principles that
underwrite our ability to engage with
the world and make sense of that world
yeah it's interesting the way you put it
because i think that finding out kind of
how you
as you say there's this serendipitous
way of falling into these things uh
which is i think kind of true for a lot
of people right they they have a one way
in which they want to do things when
they're younger and then they take the
long way up the mountain but
the the other thing is is having a
desire passion to want to do something
to understand the brain and many people
want to understand the brain but then
having the iq points and the capacity to
do that and you've written some pretty
prolific papers and so
you know having the ability to to do the
equations to do the math to be able to
do these things that had to all of just
when it kind of fit together
you know had to have been pretty
remarkable i guess for yourself to be
like you know what i would like i have
this interest and i can actually
cognitively do this i can figure this
out
what has that i guess just been like as
you you know progress you know through
your life and be like you know what yeah
i've i've done a few things i've i've
researched a few things i've figured
some things out about the brain
if you kind of look back on that how
does that just all kind of sit with you
i guess
i would imagine it's the same kind of um
sense that people have when they look
back on your on their lives
it's a long journey
and when you look at the journey in
retrospect
you are sometimes surprised by how far
you have come because in pursuing at any
one moment in that journey it all seems
very incremental so it seems
unremarkable during during the travel
um
unremarkable in the sense that things
change quite slowly and are the
reflection of the way that you've
invested in you know the early parts of
the of the journey so coming back again
to this um
early commitment to
um a formal way of expressing ideas so
you know knowing that meant that you had
to spend many years
um learning quantum physics and
probability theory which then you
immediately forgot as soon as you went
into psychiatry
at least at least you left with the
legacy
but you knew you could learn it and you
couldn't do it if necessary and of
course uh in later life it didn't become
uh necessary um but i repeat i've
forgotten everything i learned as a 20
year old but with the uh the boon the
gift of wikipedia i was soon able to get
back up to speed again so all of this
prolific writing um that uh is often
claimed to be quite inscrutable and
mathematically uh difficult to access uh
that
from my perspective is a nonsense you
can get all the maths you need uh from
wikipedia because that's exactly where i
go
it's the power of technology is
remarkable in many ways so that's great
so obviously i want to get to your your
main uh your main i guess theoretical
claim to fame if you will i mean many
claims of fame but i definitely want to
talk about the free energy principle and
just have you download that for us and
just tell us everything about it um in
as much detail as you'd like i figure
before we we get to that it might be
helpful and you can tell me what you
think of this it might be helpful to
kind of look at
a history and overview
of various brain models that we've had
and how leading up to the the current
brain model that we know and then we can
branch off to that into the kind of
bayesian brain model which which is also
uh more relevant and salient at the
moment so maybe if you could just in
your in your
from your viewpoint
how do we understand a history of
various brain models where does it kind
of first start and originate and you
know you can just kind of kind of march
us through how that gets us to current
day and what the current brain models
are
well yeah that in fact that would be i
think um
one fairly comprehensive and complete
way of understanding the free energy
principle which is just a genuine of
a long legacy of ideas that i think you
could probably trace back to the
students of plato
and shadows on caves and the like but um
for me
most clearly articulated by helmholtz in
the 19th century and sort of polymath
who
had a deep understanding of physics but
also perception and you know various
aspects of
of sentience
and many of his ideas essentially
summarized in the form of unconscious
inference
so the notion that
the brain was a constructive organ
that was
inferring the causes of its sensations
so the idea here
is that what is out there is not
directly accessible
from
the brain the skull-bound brain
but has to be
hypothesized you have to have
the cause of your sensations in mind
in order to use the sensory impressions
upon your eyes your ears and your skin
as evidence for against that hypothesis
so as andy clark would put it this is
very much
an inside out approach to perception as
opposed to an outside in view which
actually
dominated in the 20th century but then
went away again
where
the
the world impresses itself upon your
sensory epithelia and you somehow
extract information from that to get to
the conclusion oh
this is the cause of my sensations
helmholtz had a much more nuanced and
vertical or certainly by 21st century
standards vertical understanding of the
mechanics of perception
where
you had to actually generate the
hypothesis and you just used
the sensory evidence at hand to update
your beliefs adjust your
explanation for the sensations and in
that adjustment in the updating on the
inside through neural activity
you were able to produce a an
approximate or
partially faithful reproduction of what
could have caused your sensations and he
called that unconscious inference
that notion
remained in advance
through 20th century behaviorism
manifesting in many different ways
things that come to mind include
analysis by synthesis
one
key contribution from psychology was the
notion of perception explicitly as
hypothesis testing this is richard
gregory a uk psychologist's notion
again
reiterating the importance of inference
so for helmets it's really unconscious
imprints um for gregory it would have
been you know the perceptual act is
basically a test of a hypothesis that
this visual object is the best
explanation for this
pattern of sensory impressions say on my
on my retina
those ideas um
came to fruition
in um machine learning and
um
computational neuroscience
in
i would imagine the 80s and
possibly the 90s
probably best um
um
exemplified by uh the helmholtz machine
deferring back to helmholtz's original
ideas uh by uh geoffrey hinton and
colleagues and peter diane and
colleagues
so leveraging those deep insights from
helmholtz and then putting them into a
recurrent neural network or a network of
a particular kind of
kind of boltzmann machine
effectively training neural networks in
a way that we would now understand the
training of deep neural networks in deep
learning for example
to infer
we now understand that as amortization
if you were in machine learning it would
be this notion that you can train
the connectivity
of a neural network
to make sense by inferring
the causes of its inputs because you
know it's a simple move to
understand this
um
schema algorithm of the helmholtz
machine as also applicable to neuronal
networks and at that point in time
people were converging on very similar
ideas
um from a slightly different direction
they made that a predictive coding so
predictive coding
was originally devised in engineering
as the
um most efficient way to compress sound
files in the 1950s
and there's an interesting connection
here between the notion of
compressibility and efficiency
and the
statistical efficiency of a good
inference which you we may well come
back to in um
mention the conversation but at this
stage in terms of the history and the
legacy um there was in the 90s then a um
a key convergence on
the brain as an inference machine
and the brain as a predictive machine so
we then see the emergence of predictive
processing or predictive coding in
particular
perhaps just
for your listeners just to make this a
bit more explicit the predictive coding
is
defined in terms of a scheme
that is trying to resolve prediction
errors
so we have this notion now of the brain
generating top-down predictions on the
basis of its
currently preferred beliefs about the
state of the world
those predictions then compared with the
censoring input
and then the mismatch or the divergence
between the predictions and the
observations the sensory samples
are then
um denoted as a prediction error and
then that prediction error is a
broadcast deep into the brain's
hierarchy to update and revise
the hypotheses or the representations
that are generating the predictions
and i use the word generation there
because all of this machinery all this
message passing with sense making
comes under a particular generative
model that is entailed by the
architecture of the brain so you have
this picture now of the brain
broadcasting from the inside out
descending down the hierarchy
it's predictions and there's a counter
stream of ascending prediction errors
that are revising and updating the
uh the predictions
in virtue of changing the
representations
that can also be cast in bayesian terms
as
bayesian belief updating so now you've
got another
church of mathematicians theoreticians
in the game you've got you've got the
helmholtz machine you've got predictive
coding people from engineering
and also people start people like simon
mclaughlin and
raj rayo and darla ballard um
noted that
these predictive coding principles were
very apt to explain a lot of the
functional architectures of the brain
david mumford i think was a key
contributor to those ideas in the early
90s and it's not usually acknowledged as
such but you know if you go back in
very early 90s uh you know very explicit
and what proved to be
a visionary account of the neuronal
architectures that did the job of the
health health machine that did
predictive coding did hierarchical
bayesian influence
so then you have the joint emergence of
helmholtz machines machine learning the
bayesian brain hypothesis um
in
the neurosciences and predictive coding
as a particular process theory that sort
of enacted this so that was a story at
the end of the 20th century
um at which point there was an enacted
term
a turn
back to
the four e's the um
the importance of situated cognition the
importance of the fact you have a body
that your perception is an active thing
you act you actively palpate the world
at every level every sensory modality
whether it's literally feeling a way
around a dark room to confirm your
hypothesis about this is a telephone
this is the bed this is my iphone
through to
palpating the world visually through
active vision moving your eyes around
something this part of the visual scene
to test this hypothesis of that
hypothesis
so this um
embodied inactivist extended um and by
extended hair i
uh you know
one's acknowledging that a lot of your
um
cognitive abilities are um
downloadable into the environment
the key thing here though is this uh
inactive term so
how did predictive coding
the bayesian brain hypothesis
um survive the inactive turn well very
very simply that there are two ways that
you could effectively
resolve your prediction errors you could
either literally change your mind in the
good old-fashioned predictive coding
where you use your prediction errors to
drive a change of mind amazing belief
updating so the predictions now were
more fit for purpose and explaining
where the sensory inputs and thereby the
prediction as effectively canceling
themselves resolving themselves through
this hierarchical message passing in the
brain or and here's the twist you could
literally
go and re-sample the sensory input to
make it match your top-down predictions
but now you have a really simple
and
a very plausible account of active
sensing active vision uh more generally
active inference
the you know there are two ways in which
you can resolve prediction errors you
can either change your mind or change
the thing you're predicting
and thereby supplying the predicted
outcomes so this is a you know a very
simple account of action and perception
and also
um speaks to the circular causality you
know these are two processes working
hand in hand your perception is causing
action and action is causing perception
and this is how we sense make
so that um that sort of active inference
perspective
um which then i think um
[Music]
became sort of the dominant paradigm the
cognitive neurosciences under the rubric
is something called predictive
processing which was a sort of
generalization of predictive uh
predictive coding to accommodate
this inactive aspect uh of perception
so the free energy principle or on one
reading really is just a mathematical
specification of this kind of active
inference um the trick um here is um
to
cast things in a most general and
generic way as possible and by things i
just mean the resolution of prediction
errors um and
the way that one does that is by
appealing to the maths of
bayesian inference
and noting that exact basin inference is
not physically realizable
and you then have to turn to how can you
physically
realize inference of this sort
and the solution was in fact um
uh uh on offer from uh you know in the
1950s from people like richard feynman
um
sort of western um physical sciences um
but also
hints at exactly the same solution um in
the early russian literature in terms of
algorithmic complexity and comorograph
complexity
those two perspectives converge upon
exactly the same mathematical
quantity which is
a variational free energy this is not a
thermodynamic free energy this is just a
statistical way of
measuring
the
thing that you want to optimize
in any act of inference whether it's
your brain
doing inference about its sensations
or whether like richard feynman you're
trying to infer the probability
distributions of the paths of small
particles in quantum electrodynamics uh
whether you're trying to infer the
message that was sent in cryptography
for example all of these kinds of
problems
could be subsumed under one
optimization
process which is the maximization of
bayesian model evidence it's literally
the
likelihood of these data being generated
by the model that you're currently
considering
so that's
in basic systems known as
bayesian model evidence and the the
variational free energy
provides a tractable bound or
approximation to
that
that marginal likelihood or moral
evidence
which means that
in its most general form the problem of
inference
and indeed the process of inference
you know if you don't want to consider
it a problem
can be written down mathematically
as any process that either maximizes
marginal likelihood model evidence
or if you're a machine learning
maximizes free energy as an evidence
lower bound also known as an elbow elbow
um
there's a slight wrinkle here
in machine learning um they use the
negative of free energy that feynman
used so if you ever talk to physicists
that you would want to minimize your
free energy from talking to machine
learning people you want to maximize it
it doesn't matter from our point of view
the key thing is that you're just
writing down the functional the
mathematical form
of the quantity that underwrites the
process of inference that is a variation
of free energy
in optimizing either minimizing or
maximizing this
either by perception or through action
then you are effectively self-evidencing
and that's a term which i like from
jakob
that comes from philosophy that if we
understand ourselves as making sense of
the world
through a process of inference that
implicitly what we are saying is that we
are all
in the game
of garnering
sensory evidence for our models of that
world so we are literally
self-evidencing and you can just write
that down as the process of maximizing
bayesian model evidence for your model
entailed by your brain and your body
or you can write down as a physicist in
terms of minimizing a variation free
energy and that's the free energy
principle and that's roughly where we
stand at the moment
there are lots of
unanswered questions
about construction
you laid out uh very very nicely i was
it's very easy to follow there i have i
do have many follow-ups here um about a
few things i'll try and keep them very
general and kind of reframe some of what
you said
so starting with hemholtz right you were
you were talking about how there's this
inside out
and
outside in right that there's almost a
kind of dichotomy in how we understand
the world right do we understand it from
within ourselves and then based on what
you know input outputs outputs input
whatever way you want to describe it
is it and maybe that's just how it's
falling out is it always kind of in
these two
uh camps or categories or is there a
third or fourth way is there another way
where we could see
a kind of mixture where it's not
exclusively outputs from the environment
excuse me inputs from the environment
and then we output is there some way in
which we can understand that there's a
third way or a fourth way or other ways
in which these are combined and where it
isn't just input output right it's not
just a kind of zeros and ones kind of
thing is there another way in which
there's
uh an integration of them or or
potentially some way of the
phenomenology of how we're experiencing
things
is it is it always this kind of way and
how it lays out because it seems
throughout time as you were saying with
hemholtz there's this
um there is this kind of dichotomy where
people will kind of look at the the
economy here and then all the way to the
machine learning stuff in the 90s it
kind of does this
oscillating back and forth between where
do we put the emphasis where do we put
it first so i guess that's one that's
one component
uh the second uh piece here when you
were talking about if i understand this
is
the free energy principle from what
you're saying
sounds like it's the kind of
quantitative and statistical
ways of understanding the bayesian model
of the brain
and so they're kind of seen in tandem
along with the active interference which
you which you explained
connected with that there's this
emphasis on perception especially with
humans
so i wonder with the predictive types of
elements that you were discussing
where do we this might be a little bit
further out and maybe some of this may
be hard to know all of this is very
human
i wonder if we understand some of these
things for non-human
brains as well such as with chimps or
bonobos or or even other types of it
might not even be
with primates it could be what do we
understand about how potentially
these workings of the brain could be for
other brains that are non-human so
trying to look at a kind of evolutionary
structure and model and then finally um
uh
curious about if you have any
thoughts about
you mentioned philosophy and as you were
saying that there was this kind of
in the 21st century now
not just an over emphasis on the brain
but how the brain and how it works is
distributed through the body and how the
body is a necessary component which
automatically always makes me think of
uh philosophy of merlou ponti who also
thought a lot about perception
and in many ways had very technical ways
of thinking about perception he talked a
lot about eyes he talked a lot about
sensations and i wonder
his estimation he was looking at the
phenomenology of things of how
do we understand experiences
through the body that the body is a
necessary or or is a prerequisite of
sorts as a type of bridge for
understanding our various perceptions um
so
those are my follow-ups i don't want to
throw it all at you at once but
any any thoughts about any of that i
guess right you you've just thrown all
three massive issues at once yes yes
those wonderful
we have to say at least something about
each one of them yes please so in order
then so the um is there a third way that
does not
um commit to an inside out um
information extraction or
sorry
an inside out
construction versus a constructive
constructivist approach versus an
outside in extractionist approach
and yeah
in a sense
that just is the bayesian brain that
just is
um the free energy principle and active
inference that is entailed by the free
energy principle because that is
explicitly saying you have to have this
two-way traffic
and this emerges in
you know
many different levels so for example
um we've already talked about this sort
of recurrent
um two-way traffic of message passing in
the brain from the
sensory parts of the brain to the deeper
hierarchically
organized um
levels of a the brain's generative model
this whole belief updating this whole
bayesian mechanics depends upon this
counter stream of top-down predictions
and bottom-up
bottom-up prediction errors on a
predictive coding architecture or view
um so you've got this recurrence you've
got the circular causality for free but
even more generally as as you intimated
in the third issue um you brought to the
table here the the you know
the very um dependency of perception on
action
and action on on perception so put
simply um
i have to perceive and infer in order to
plan what to do next so action is
predicated on my perceptual synthesis
and making sense of the current state of
my body and the world and what i want to
query the world about the you know what
kinds of questions what kind of
information do i want to get
by deploying my uh sense organs
so
that is you're almost self-evident but
in the same way that actually depends
upon perception perception also depends
on action what i see depends upon where
i look or you know how
i place my um
skin in relation to an object that i'm
trying to palpate
so there's this unbreakable
um circular causality and two-way street
between action and perception so i would
submit that your your
quest for the third way as has
has been delivered
for you by
um by the inactivist term by the an
activist application of predicted uh
your two predictive coding to the
brazilian brain hypothesis um
at the turn of the century i think you
know that is the third way you can't
tease these two things apart really
um so that that should be comforting um
and it should resolve any angst that
wouldn't be seen
it's very satisfying yes
now the second issue
what was the second issue the second one
was about about the in non-human brains
oh yes evolutionary construct yeah the
way that you ask that question makes me
realize i've made a fundamental mistake
here in uh in terms of telling the the
story and unpacking the narrative of um
of
the of active inference um in its 21st
century version and so most of what i've
just
talked about in terms of um the
mechanics of inference and um
optimal action
could be applied to a thermostat or a
virus
so
i think i would actually put the
question the other way around and
perhaps that's how you actually meant uh
the question i'm sure that we'll come to
this later on um
you know what is what is special about
the human brain
that um uh has some unique and
definitive properties that you were not
found in a thermostat that you would not
find in a virus you would not find in a
mouse you possibly wouldn't even find it
in um
in your
most loved pet or you know some of our
closer um
um
uh companions and uh say monkeys you
know an evolutionary um
view um
so i i think that that's a you know
that's the the direction the question um
should be approached it's less you know
what's special about uh mice it's more
how do you make the move from mice to
men under this kind of architecture so
most of the work that
that we do is at a much lower level it's
just trying to understand the
fundamentals of active self-organization
under through the lens of sense-making
and imprints that can be written down
as a process
that usually is actually emergent uh an
emergent property of any self-organizing
system that preserves a distinction
between itself and the environment that
doesn't decay dissolve dissipate die um
so you know
looking really trying to explain how on
earth does a virus survive
and
what
must it do in terms of this
circular third way exchange between the
inside and the outside to preserve its
very boundaries and de-marketing from
its external milieu
without worrying too much about
what it is to be human so we haven't got
anywhere near as marx sounds like a set
of questions yet
we are not talking about um bayesian
beliefs as propositional beliefs that
you and i might hold and be able to
articulate we are not talking about
qualitative experience
we are just talking about the mechanics
of brief updating on
neuronal circuits neural circuits
chemical circuits electrochemical
circuits
that we see in every kind of biotic and
possibly even non-biotic
self-organization so that's a deep
question um
you know
and the answers to that question take
you through a series of
natural kinds of things
that
all are doing some
um inference of a a possibly a weak kind
um and can all be
if you like um
described in terms of an ontology of
generative models if you remember before
we're talking about the
underlying importance of a generative
model
in supplying
the architecture under which you
generate your hypothesis your top-down
predictions and you use basic this is
the thing that you are securing evidence
for
which means that um if there is a
difference between mice and men
then there has to be something
quintessentially different between the
genitive models that you and i employ
to navigate actively our world and those
that might and flies um use um and
once one starts to think about it you
know one might ask what is the
difference between a um
a
let's take viruses flies are a little
bit too sophisticated what's the
difference between a virus and a mouse
and what's the difference between a
mouse and me or you um and
normally the story goes that
it's all to do with the ability to plan
it may sound very very simple
but you know
once you've heard the argument you know
it is actually a very simple argument
but it's also quite a compelling um
argument and has has a degree of
expansion scope in the sense that um the
thing that distinguishes between a
thermostat or a virus or some single
celled organism
succumbing to nutrition gradients
through chemotaxis
relative to something like a mouse that
does stuff in anticipation of
consequences is the ability of the mouse
to plan the mouse can think about and
select those actions that have
consequences and that's absolutely
profound when it comes to writing down
or thinking about the genitive model
that that mouse is using it tells you
immediately
that the mouse
has a model of the consequences of its
action
if it has a model of the consequences of
its action given that the consequences
occur after the action
then it also has a model of the future
so it now has a model that has a
temporal depth
and this can be contrasted with the
thermostat or virus it does not the
thermostat doesn't have a model
of the future it doesn't have an
explicit um
hypothesis or question in its internal
machinery of the kind well what would
happen if i switch this heat making
device on or not it just responds
reflexively in the moment but the mouse
will have a much more elaborate
model sometimes described as a model
with temporal depth that frees you from
the moment but also crucially
underwrites the ability to plan and
thereby select from one plan or another
plan one course of action relative to
another course of action
that endows
that little agent
with
agency because now it is selecting
amongst a number of different courses of
action
that are entertained
and can be supported by its genetic
model so now together you've got this
sort of um move from a thermostat to a
mouse
that entails the notion of agency
and temporal depth
simply because this generative moral has
the ability to model the consequences of
action so that's one move does that give
you qualitative experience does that
give you propositional beliefs does that
do we have mouse philosophers who spend
their time
puzzling about why they see red and does
one mouse see the same red as another
mouse no absolutely not so we still
haven't answered the question um what's
the difference between a mouse and a man
um
just sorry just on the on the mouse
thing it sounds like what you're
describing in the ability to have some
uh planning
sounds like there's at least a low level
type of what we would call executive
functioning though where there's
abilities of plan organized sequence
right which we normally see in the
prefrontal cortex for humans
but it seems like it's a very low level
uh ability whereas as we get to humans
there's a much less deeper level of
abstraction that we understand is this
is this about right now that's that's
exactly and absolutely right so
all i am talking about here um is
exactly the the
prefrontal cortex
um and all the attendant uh executive
machinery uh right down through
uh supplementary motor area premonitor
courtesy metacortis down to the brain
stem and all uh and all the um the
executive components that are
responsible for executing the plans that
are elaborated through selecting the
right course of action in the prefrontal
cortex so that's exactly right and
that's what mice can do um you know they
don't have quite as well developed a
prefrontal cortex as we do but they have
the equivalent um
you know the equivalent capacity to
execute plans
simply because they need to have that
because
they have plans in their head but having
plans in their head is a remarkable
capacity you know a thermostat i repeat
does not need to have a plan uh you know
it just responds as a reflex as do many
you know forms of lower life or biotic
self-organization
so you also used um you know a
hierarchically deeper levels of
abstraction i think that's the absolute
key here and and then
this question would be well what are you
hierarchically abstracting
and i think most people would answer
well
you are now
creating models of your executive
process
so now a mouse has the ability to plan
and to execute those plans by selecting
the plans that are most plausible in the
sense that they will resolve
surprise or prediction error or free
energy in the future we call that
expected free energy uh technically um
which has some interesting aspects to it
um
so
the the mouse then
has this ability so what ability do we
have because of our more evolved
prefrontal cortexes with these deeper
levels of abstraction well it could
simply be
to entertain the hypothesis that i am a
person who is now selecting
these plans and it is me who is actually
executing these plans
so you know
to a generative model that now
entertains the hypothesis the belief the
representation
that it's me doing these things it is me
who is embodied it is me who is the
agent
so an agent doesn't need to know that it
is an agent to actually plan and execute
those plans in the same way the
thermostat doesn't know it's a
thermostat and then it's even acting
so i think that the levels of
abstraction you're referring to here are
exactly
the abstraction and the plausible
hypothesis that in fact i am
an object and indeed i am the subject of
my own observations and actions and
having that hypothesis as part of the
genetic model
now has to
be explained and how can it be explained
how could it be that i now have a
better
generative model or explanation of my
sensorium that has been actively
constructed
um simply by having this notion that i
am a person and i think there are you
know quite simple answers to that
because of course it's not just i am a
person i'm a person in this police state
or that police state or that emotional
state
or this uh
intentional proposition state and once i
recognize myself to be in that state and
implicitly now i have a degree
of
qualitative experience of my inference
lowering the hierarchy
then i can now
bring to bear and contextualize all my
message passing and inference
conditional upon my now recognized state
so for example if i know that i am
anxious or i am embarrassed
i know that
there will be certain kinds of
information to which i would be paying
attention um there will be certain sort
of autonomic actions that i would uh
normally be
engaging in this context of being
embarrassed or being frightened such as
cardio acceleration or paying particular
attention to um auditory and visual
streams for example
so there is there is an easy to argue
benefit of for having these higher
levels of deep more deeply abstracted
representations and explanations
for
the active inference and all the message
passing that's going on
that's going on underneath and i think
you know
if you go right to the top of the
hierarchy to the very highest form of
human life which would be a philosopher
what you find there
are representations and hypotheses that
just are qualia and qualitative
experience so you know this is touching
on now um something which david charmans
has
popularized as a the meta problem or the
meta hard problem
is why do we puzzle about our
qualitative experiences you know ice
don't do that
so once special aspects of our genitive
models
can explain the very fact that we can
entertain notions like being a zombie
for example or thought experiments like
brain in a vat the very fact that we can
entertain these counter factual
outlandish hypotheses about self
is the gift if you like of having these
deeply abstracted representations of how
we engage with the world you know
first of all just um
having a representation of me or
selfhood and then you know
me as an actively inferring agent that
must in some sense have some internal
action over
the way in which i secure the evidence
and test my hypotheses i'm trying to
work here to um assumption which i think
mark uh sounds may have um talked about
which is you know
what underwrites
the the feeling part the um the you know
the quality of experience
that
the philosophers talk about in terms of
qualia um
the um
the the
the
essence that we think
we can uh um
entertain and have discourse about
that perhaps um a mouse might not be
able to talk about it may have but he
wouldn't be able to recognize it or talk
about it it's not just not there it just
can't see that kind of thing in the same
sense that a blind person can't see
color it may well be that a mouse just
not does not have these hierarchical
levels of abstraction so it's just not
perceivable in the sense of helmholtz um
you know you have to have it in mind
before you can
before you can you can sense it
the argument
the answer that somebody like mark
sobres i think a lot of people would
would bring to the table here
is the notion of um
um
confidence or precision or a
representation of uncertainty in one's
beliefs and getting that right and
that basically
entails
a kind of mental action so now we're
talking about action not on the outside
not
autonomic actions like secreting
something or
cardio acceleration
and we're not talking about motor
actions motor reflexes moving my limbs
around with my stride and muscles we're
talking about a covert internalized
action
whereas very very high levels of a
hierarchy or very deep levels perhaps
you know at the center of the brain
from uh mark services perspective
have an influence on the belief updating
that underwrites the action selection
and that influence is really
a
statement that we're able to represent
our own beliefs we have beliefs about
beliefs the particular example here
is um we have certain beliefs
about our beliefs that pertain to the
uncertainty
so um
if you have in mind the simple
mathematical description of a belief as
a probability distribution so
when people talk about basically i
repeat they don't they're not talking
about sort of ideological or theological
commitment
you know they're just talking about
um the the brain as a sentient artifact
that is somehow encoding a probability
distribution and invariably
these kinds of beliefs these bayesian
beliefs of conditional probability
distributions have two
cardinal aspects they have a location
so that the most likely thing i believe
or the basic belief entails
is
designated by the peak of the
probability distribution and there's
another shape parameter um another
aspect of this
probability density or distribution
which is its spread or dispersion and
that's usually understood in terms of
uncertainty so very broad distribution
means that all of these things could be
in play as a very sharp very precise
distribution means that i'm pretty
confident that it's just
underneath this very sharp distribution
so that precise that that precision is a
really important
um
attribute of a belief and if parts of
the brain
now have beliefs about beliefs they are
now predicting precision predicting
predictability
and that may well be the thing
that um
calls for
cover mental action and the
need for
recognizing that i'm in this belief
state or this state of uncertainty on
that state of uncertainty and then i can
now deploy
the uh the appropriate beliefs about
beliefs or predictions of predictability
or predictions of precision
yeah it's interesting on that last point
because what you're sounding like you're
describing is this this type of
metacognition that's interested in our
own epistemology and also our ontology
as well right that we're very concerned
about our beliefs and how we how we have
these beliefs about them or even things
about our own existence or things about
us who we are as beings one other point
i wanted to make about the abstraction
piece is that
i totally agree obviously but i think
even even more
uh miraculous if you will or more
wonderful is the fact that for humans
not only can we have these
levels of abstraction but i always think
of this example of like you know i can
know
that i'm thinking about a concept or i
can know that someone else is
potentially thinking about a concept
right there's this way of abstracting
with the other
but even further if you take works of
fiction let's say let's say i'm reading
a novel and the central character
is thinking about a thought he had in a
dream that he had there's and i'm the
one reading that thought that someone
wrote you have like six layers of
abstraction there right this is very big
big big wide lens of things
which is incredible it's incredible our
mind doesn't you know fold up you know
because of how complicated or complex
that is it's in and i don't know if
other
animals on the planet
can you know read novels and get the
whole contract or if people watch a
movie right and they can see or observe
all of these things
um so it's very interesting about the
abstraction and i liked how you linked
with the various components of executive
functioning for for detailing that
we've talked a lot about the bayesian
brain and we've mentioned many
components of it
maybe we can give for for listeners the
kind of overview of the bayesian brain
and then that will kind of dovetail into
the free energy principle and i'll let
you just i'll give you a lot of runway
for that you can you can talk all about
that so my under you correct me here if
i'm wrong my limited understanding of
the bayesian brain is that the brain is
essentially equipped with an internal
model of the environment and that gives
us a plan for how do we create sensory
observer observations from hidden states
right that's one way of saying it and
that there are these hidden variables
that are from a prior distribution
you could say maybe i don't know if
you want to use the freudian term the
unconscious we can come to freud at some
point um and then also that these
sensory observations
are have a distribution conditional on
the hidden state so then you have these
priors and you have a likelihood
combined to infer the hidden state given
the observations so i think the
clarifying point here is that these
aren't specific claims about priors and
likelihoods for
an individual but more so on the
consistency of them that's my
very limited scope of the bayesian brain
so maybe
kind of branch off of that and just kind
of give us the full overview of what we
mean by the basin brain priors
likelihood hidden states and then we can
jump into the uh the free energy
principle
right and well i mean that description
was
spot on in itself so all i need to do is
to connect what you've just described
okay what we're talking about
so
i think that we basically have done the
bayesian brain uh and we've done the
finest and most delicate aspects of
of the bayesian brain under a hierarchal
genetic model when you started talking
about the you know the six degrees of
hierarchical embedding and i'm glad you
used the word metacognition so that's
what i was trying to imply i was talking
about beliefs about beliefs this is
exactly it and it is this hierarchical
uh recursive embedding which is quite
remarkable you know uh i can't really
use the word fall down or unfold but but
certainly you know at about six degrees
of um of recursion uh my brain gives up
and i think i'm at that point yes that
may be the explanation for the better
hard problem that you know
even philosophers can't quite handle
that and that
residual puzzlement you know uh inspires
us to try and get to the seventh or the
or the eighth but it is exactly that
sort of bleeds about beliefs about
beliefs the other key thing you just
brought to the table before um just
unpacking the bayesian brain
in
um the language and the setting that
we've already established um you brought
another really key thing to the table
which is inference about others
and i was tempted to say well perhaps
that's one aspect of the third way that
we haven't talked about that we haven't
spoken about and perhaps we should have
spoken a lot because
everything that we've spoken about thus
far
would work for a single agent in a
universe that did not have anything else
like it in that universe it's just
making sense of the universe um
but of course most of the interesting
questions um in terms of
self-understanding are in light of or
contextualized by the need to understand
others so when you're we're now moving
from the bayesian brain and beyond that
to the embodied bayesian brain which is
the third issue that we've still yet to
talk about um but now to
multiple bayesian brains
in an ensemble
all ex all trying to infer each other
and that brings some really interesting
questions to the table about
self-understanding in relation to others
understanding and there could be an
argument
the the need for selfhood
or a an explicit ability to recognize i
am a self
and to have at least a minimal selfhood
is just a product of being a being
required
to
disambiguate
the causes of my sensations in terms of
did i cause that or did you cause that
or perhaps more practically um
more relevant would be uh during very
early early neonatal experience did did
i cause that or did mother cause that so
mother being the key other
and this being able to
first of all recognize
that
mother is actually
an object
out there that is distinct from me is a
great move to be able to do and
something that takes you on sort of a
long time for it for a neonate to and
not every dna
you know recognizes that and can learn
the appropriate genetic models that
explains
interactions or
our interactions with mum
in terms of mum being a creature
because once you realize that mum is a
creature or an object out there
then the natural hypothesis might be to
enter well perhaps i am a creature and
why would you need to do that well you
need to do that between disambiguate did
i cause that or did mom cause that
so that
elemental
theory of mind the ability to
distinguish between the cons
between
the causes of sensations in terms of
self versus other
may be
unique to
creatures that
have a universe or an environment that
is populated by creatures like them such
as you and me so i think this is a
really key um aspect of this sort of
self-evidencing self-evidencing yes but
it's in the context of a whole world
comprised of things which are just like
me so i have to now be very skilled at
differentiating me from you and in so
doing of course
that
pressure is only
convinced if you are sufficiently
similar to me and cause the same kinds
of sounds and relative touches and
sensations that i could cause i don't
need to do that given that you are
physically
very similar to me but if you're that
similar to me i can now use
my genitive models my explanations of
the world to explain uh which i would
normally use to explain
my autonomic dispositions and you know
my bodily sensations all my movements i
can now use those prior beliefs
selections of the plans that we were
talking about our intentions
to explain
your intentions or more specifically to
explain your behavior your facial
configuration your
micro expressions your physical stance
um in terms of
your intentions which would be the
intentions i would have to have in order
to witness and you know to manifest the
same kind of observable behaviors so i
think that you know that's a really
important thing you brought to the table
and you know
in terms of
self
selfhood and self-evidencing
or being particularly acute um and
important um in the context of
your a world that has
um
has a culture uh that is born of the
fact that we are we populate that world
with lots of con specifics and we have a
you know
we have a shared economy in which to do
that
so
um i just wanted to put that on the
table because it's a really important
thing when it comes to sort of personal
exchanges
yeah absolutely
but the back to the basic brain well you
just summarized it i mean
i don't
you've done all the heavy lifting there
i think it's probably
best just to say out loud at this point
there is nothing that the bayesian brain
brings to the table we haven't already
spoken about it's just a way one way of
articulating um the kind of sense making
where we have say prediction errors
ascending the hierarchy from from the
sensory cortex and sensory parts of our
brain and updating
representations
um
that would be
in a bayesian sense
regarded as posterior beliefs so
what i'm going to do now is just tell
the bayesian brain story from the point
of view as somebody who likes to talk
about predictive coding so we've already
established predictive coding predicted
coding i should just add
if i was talking to an engineer i
wouldn't use the word predictive coding
i would i would use the phrase bayesian
filtering the simplest instance of a
bayesian filter in something called a
kalman filter
which is used widely in state estimation
so
predictive coding just is kalman
filtering of an extended and non-linear
form sometimes known as an extended
kalman bucy filter of a hierarchical
sort um so these things are all the same
but different people like to use
different language so what would how
would you understand bayesian inference
from the point of view of predictive
coding well as you say bayesian
inference is just the process of belief
updating
how would you articulate that from the
bayesian brain hypothesis well that
update is just an update to your
bayesian beliefs your conditional
probability distributions
prior to seeing some
data
to some beliefs after or apostle so
you're just updating your prior belief
to your posterior belief you're
literally changing your mind you're just
moving through changing neural activity
or
weights or connection strengths in your
brain
uh you're changing
the
implicit or encoded bayesian belief from
a prior belief before you saw the data
to a posterior belief after you saw the
data
and that movement from one belief to
another belief literally changing your
mind um is the updating that is driven
by the prediction errors
so the next question then would be well
um
what is the nature of that updating um
as we if you like mix together the pry
belief and the light the information
afforded by the likelihood of these data
to produce the posterior belief so
that's just to explain to the listeners
why there were three kinds of beliefs
there's all likelihood distribution um a
prior belief and a posterior belief
and really the likelihood um
if you mix together the prior belief and
the likelihood that you get the
posterior out so the likelihood stands
in for the um the pressure or the forces
applied to changing your mind
that drive a change in mind or the
belief updating
that are afforded by the data
and this is i think a useful view um
because
it allows us to come back to this notion
of precision
um
it's difficult to do uh without a white
board or a black ball
but
let's have a go because this is i think
a really intuitive and really important
um
important observation which brings us
back there's a mental action of the
notion of predictions of precision so if
i had a very very
vague imprecise prior belief
uh and i got i had some very definitive
very precise sensory evidence
that could be of an elemental sort like
the
particular pattern of visual impressions
in a well-lit room or it could indeed a
more abstract level be some definitive
information from wikipedia but if it's
very precise
then that precise likelihood will have a
very sharp narrow distribution and will
pull the soft flat prior distribution
much closer to the likelihood
so that my posterior now is now
dominated by the shape and the form of
the likelihood
so i've induced a much greater degree of
belief updating i've changed my mind
considerably more than i would have done
simply because i ascribed a greater
precision to these data so it had a much
more precise likelihood
conversely if i have a very very precise
prime belief that it's based on lots and
lots of experience
then it's going to be much less
sensitive to any likelihood or any
belief updating
so
my poster is going to be
if you like tethered to my prime belief
as i change my mind and i move from my
prior to my post area when seeing the
evidence doing my basic leaf update
according to baserule
i will move a much smaller distance from
the uh from the prime belief so the
precision afforded both the prior belief
and the likelihood in fact it's the
balance the ratio of the two becomes a
really important quantity in any
bayesian brain or any bayesian scheme
in engineering this would be the kalman
gain for example is how much gain do i
afford prediction errors in
updating my estimate of the hidden state
that i can't see
um
so um
that place is this this notion of of the
the encoding of and the predictions of
the optimization of precision center
stage in the bayesian brain
you see this in many many guises
you can see it in the context of
multi-sensory integration
so how much precision do i for do i
afford
the
visual evidence relative to the auditory
um sensory data
if i'm in a very very
well lit room i might ascribe much more
precision to the visual information and
that will dominate over my belief
updating and my beliefs will be driven
by what i see and what i hear
but if i reduce the precision of the of
that visual information those visual
prediction errors and switch off the
light so now in the dark room that now
becomes very imprecise and now the most
precise influences of my posterior
beliefs are going to be the the auditory
modalities i'm going to listen very very
carefully in a dark room i'm going to
pay attention to the auditory sensations
not the visual sensations
so that i've used the word attention
deliberately because this from a
psychological perspective what we're
talking about is deploying the precision
in the right way in the right context
just is attention
it's what we attend to and that
attention can operate at any level in
the hierarchy can be sort of
attention-grabbing stuff in a particular
quadrant of my visual field
some flutter which is unexplained that
can now draw attention at a very low
level in the hierarchy or i could be
deploying attention to a very very high
level of
the hierarchy you know in terms of who
i'm going to listen to next or who i'm
going to place some epistemic trust in
what news channel
am i going to select next so this
process of
selecting
by
assigning or affording precision to this
or that
is
this exactly this mental action that we
were talking about before it's just
deploying attention in the right kind of
way and that attention mediated through
the precision of either prior or
likelihood beliefs has a profound effect
on the degree to which i change my mind
so it's a really important aspect of
this belief updating at the at the
neuronal level the predictive coding
theory it has two
classes of neurons which is the
prediction neurons and the prediction
era neurons you've mentioned this
already but i'm just asking that the
neuronal level this is what's happening
within the neurons there you have these
two classes of neurons that are
essentially weeding out
is this a prediction
and how are we parsing out some of the
prediction error this is what's
happening at the neuronal level
absolutely and
it's nice you sort of um ask that
question because that allows us to
connect um this um predictions of uh
precision or predictability um that
underwrites optimal belief updating and
bayesian inference
to
pharmacology and to the kinds of uh
neurochemicals that may be apparent say
in things like schizophrenia or
indepression
or autistic uh autism
and um asd
and also implicate um
all the drugs that have a psycho active
aspect from psychedelics through to the
kinds of drugs that people prescribe
um for say psychotic depression so yeah
let's just unpack that so now we've got
we've done the the bayes rule and the
bayesian brain with in our minds eye
free probability distributions or being
mixed together in the right kind of way
according to their dispersion or their
width um
but now let's say well
how would that be implemented in a in a
bayesian brain well the implementation
just is a common filter it's just a
predictive coding what would that look
like well on one view as you say it
would just involve um
two kinds of populations one encoding
the prediction error and the other
encoding the expectations or the
hypotheses representations that are
generating the predictions that are sent
down
to form the prediction error so
this again speaks to this recurrent
message passing between the the
prediction
neurons sometimes ascribed to the
cells that live
at a slightly greater depth on the
surface of the brain the cortical layers
relative or distinct from populations
occurring in the prediction error
sometimes described as superficial
pyramidal cells simply because they live
very much closer to the uh
to the surface of the brain so you've
got this sort of reciprocal exchange of
messages
where you can think of the deep
pyramidal cells of the deeper cells
as encoding
the position of the posterior
so
let's say some information comes in
from the sensory epithelia
there is a prior
belief encoded by the activity of a deep
population of deep cells
and they provide a prediction that is
now
not an apt explanation for this new
information that's coming in there is a
prediction error the prediction error is
reported by the superficial pyramidal
cells
that is then sent forward to change the
deep environmental cells at the next
level
this is just the belief updating
so the uh and now the
deep pyramidal cells that were
previously encoding the prior
expectation expectation here is just use
as a word uh to mean the mathematical
average or the most likely uh
value of our
of our belief
then the
the
prediction errors can now be seen as
doing this changing your mind doing the
brief updating just by driving the
activity of the depravital cells
in proportion to the precision of the
prediction error
so if you ascribe a lot of
newsworthiness a lot of precision
to these kinds of prediction errors from
this modality in this point in time
um then what you are doing is
effectively boosting them and you know
increasing their potency
their gain or their drive so that they
cause a bigger
belief updating or shift or changing
your mind simply because they're driving
the
deep parabola cells
towards the likelihood uh to a greater
extent and away from the prior than um
than had the prediction errors have been
been assigned a much lower precision
so what would precision look like from a
um
a neurophysiologist or a pharmacologist
perspective well it's just the
excitability of these superficial
parallel cells encoding prediction
errors
so that tells you immediately anything
that changes the excitability
or the sensitivity
of populations encoding prediction
errors
under a predictive coding scheme
is going to be
the
physical or biophysical realization of
the of this precision
which then you ask well what kinds of
things could change the excitability or
the postsynaptic game sometimes
used in neurophysiology well
in the brain there are certain brain
chemicals or neurotransmitters whose
role is just to modulate the gain of
these
kinds of cells
and what you then ask them what kinds of
neurotransmitters as well ones which
many people have heard of um so classic
uh
neurotransmitters of a neuromodulatory
sort would be things like adrenaline
oxytocin
a certain oxytocin therefore for a
particular reason that
dopamine would probably be the uh the
sort of the post child of this kind of
neurotransmitter well there are others
um you know
acetylcholine or cholinergic
neurotransmission
um
serotonergic neurotransmission of the
kind that's influenced by psychedelics
and psilocybin for example
so you can see immediately if you've
heard of any of these drugs you will
know that they can have a profound
effect on the way you feel or the way
that you update your beliefs or respond
to changes in sensory contingencies or
changes in life circumstances
and of course it is these
neurotransmitter systems
that are responsible for setting the
gain
and computationally thereby the
precision or the ability of prediction
errors to drive bleep updating higher in
the hierarchy that are used in a
therapeutic and also recreational
recreational setting
yeah it's really important how you're
connecting everything here with not only
the two classes of neurons but then also
bringing in the neurotransmitters and
how they're also functioning here as
well
i want to
give you a
lot of runway here and many of this will
start to tie in together so hopefully
listeners will be able to see that but
give me your
detailed explanation and analysis
and uh
exploration of the free energy principle
uh just lay it all out for us just
describe what it is how it works how it
functions and then how it connects with
you know many of the things we've
already discussed i'm sure it will come
up with active interference predictive
coding theory and bayesian brain model
so just tell us
your free energy principle what it is
and how it works and you can be as
detailed as you would like
right
i guess i don't want to exhaust you no
no it's great i i it's funny because i i
feel like at this point
we've done all the warm-up so now we can
get to the to the to the entree we get
to the main course here so tell us about
the the free energy principle from uh
from uh from yourself
right yeah i i have to confess you know
that warm-up was probably um a more
substantive a pair of teeth than you
might imagine
we've done we've done 90 of the heavy
in the sense that um the free energy
principle um
provides a first principal account of
the of the mechanics that we have been
talking about
so
um i'll try and explain what the free
energy principle is in a second but
perhaps just preface that by
noting
that
it plays the same role um as hamilton's
principle of least action and you could
even argue uh the theories uh that um
undergo natural selection evolution
so
in and of themselves they don't do much
heavy lifting of an explanatory sort you
know for example knowing natural
selection is a principle by which you
and i are here it doesn't tell me
anything about why you've got eyes or a
nice little beard or you've got your
particular accent it tells me nothing
about that right it just tells me there
is a mechanism
as to how these things could have
emerged
so the free energy principle is a little
bit like that i'll give you another
analogy hammerkill's principle of least
action so it's a
a generic i would say foundational um
um principle that underwrites all known
physics
arguably
and yet it doesn't tell me how on earth
i going to throw this ball
i can if you tell me all the processes
all the mechanics and the initial
conditions of a particular instance of
bald throwing i can certainly compute
the trajectory of the ball but in and of
itself it doesn't it just tells you the
principles underwrite the actual process
of ball throwing i'd actually have to
become an expert in ball throwing
to actually realize and apply the method
of uh or the principle of least action
and i use the principle-released action
because um the free energy principle is
just a principle of least action
so it's a principle that could be read
as a method that could be applied to a
particular instance or circumstance of
self-organization or active inference
but you're going to have to write down
all the actual
aspects of that circumstance
in order to make the principle do any
work and in a sense what we've been
talking about in terms of
various perspectives
afforded by predictive curling the basin
brain embodiment um
all of these
are really um
process theories accounts of a
realization of the free energy principle
so i just put it saying the scene you
know and to qualify my statement that
you know
the starter was actually the main deal
because
all the hard work and the heavy lifting
is really in testing these different
process theories and understanding how
the free energy principle operates in
this particular context with this
particular creature this particular
institution this particular
aspect of self-organization
so uh having said that then what is a
free energy principle well it sort of
transmuted to a certain extent depending
upon how the story is told
um
nowadays one would really uh tell the
story from the point of view of a
physicist
trying to
understand
self-organization
under a particular constraint and that
constraint is that you are
trying to understand the
the dynamics and the physics
and the principles of least action
that would apply
to
something now that may sound really
trivial um
but it's in fact quite
an important
starting point if you're if you want to
talk about something
then you have to say well what defines a
thing
what separates the thing
from nothing or from something else
and immediately you get into the game of
defining
how you'd separate the states of a thing
from something else the states that were
external say to that thing
and this leads you into the world of
markov blankets and conditional
independences statistical devices that
enable you to say that there is some
independence or
disintegrability between the states of
this thing and the states of everything
else and
basically what happens is when you apply
hamilton's principle of least action
to
the dynamics
of
joint systems that possess
um a markov blanket that separates the
thing we usually call it a particle from
something else
then what emerges is basically a
bayesian brain or the bayesian mechanics
that could be applied to a brain but
also to a thermostat all to a virus
which is why i was saying before the way
that we deal with things is in a much uh
we usually start you know with very very
simple systems so to cut a long story
short um what you are doing
is
um
engaging
the same
sort of um
questions um and formalisms that people
in physics would engage if they're
trying to understand uh non-equilibrium
steady-state dynamics and why is that
different from 20th century physics well
because most of 20th century physics
were all about equilibrium systems it's
all about sort of idealized gases it's
all about um second laws that apply to
closed systems and by closed systems
what i mean is that you've got this sort
of system of exchangeable particles
that's in a heat puff or in a heat
reservoir
and i use the word heat bath here
because
the question that somebody interested in
open systems would be asking where did
the heat bath come from
and what's outside the heat path and how
on earth did the heat valve maintain
itself so you now started to ask
questions that people in the life
sciences have been asking people like um
varela in terms of autophagus you know
how on earth
does the boundary from my perspective
the markov blanket the heat buff that
contains the idealized internal states
of enquiry that define the particle in
question of the system in question how
on earth is that maintained
and even more simply its very existence
and persistence
what does that imply
and if one just follows through the
maths that you would normally apply
to
an uncontained
set states of the system
to a contained
set of states that are contained within
a markov blanket that comprises sensory
and active states and then what you end
up with
is
a functional expression or functional
form
for the dynamics
that is formally exactly the same that
you would find in the other kinds of
mechanics so you know you can
think of
the free energy principle as just
basically introducing
a different kind of mechanics that is a
complement to
on the one hand classical mechanics that
would apply to heavenly bodies and
massive bodies where there were very few
random fluctuations in play because
they're so big or cold
on the one hand
the second kind of mechanics that you
get in the absence of a markov blanket
would be statistical mechanics
thermodynamics uh fluctuation theorems
that apply to lots of very hot very
small things that don't have
conservative dynamics where the random
fluctuations dominate over the classical
conservative dynamics of
newtonian mechanics
you can even apply it to quantum
mechanics the move here is just to work
with the complex root of probability
distributions bayesian beliefs
the wave function squared now becomes
the bayesian belief
but you don't have any bayesian nus
in either
in any of the classical mechanics
or the quantum mechanics all the
statistical
stochastic mechanics and that's because
none of these mechanics have a
separation between the inside and the
outside
and it comes back to something you
mentioned earlier on which is the notion
of hidden states
and you remember and i should have
picked up on that when you were
framing uh bayesian uh thinking so the
whole point of bayesian thinking is
there has to be an insight and an
outside
so there has to be observable
consequences of causes that are
unobservable
so
you know before you can even talk about
inference there has to be something
about which you are making an inference
and there has to be
some data
some observable consequences of these
hidden states or hidden causes uh that
now you plug into your bayes rule and
you know we can then go back to the
story about
moving a posterior from a prior given
the likelihood of your observable
sensory data
but just standing back from that
construct
means you now have to have a physics
that makes a distinction between stuff
on the inside the internal states of
the system
and stuff that is hidden
states that are hidden
that
will now support a bayesian inference
and of course this is exactly what is
supplied by the markov blanket so the
markov blanket is a set of states and
intervenes between the inside and the
outside and literally surrounds forms a
blanket a shield a veil of a statistical
sword sort that encompasses and shrouds
the internal states so now what plays
out on the surface on the blanket states
are now the sensory data
the
the observations of sensory evidence
that are reporting
the influence of the external states on
the outside that are hidden
from the internal states because they
are behind the mark of blanket
so you have to have a markov blanket
that separates the inside from the
outside before you can have a basic
mechanics but once you um
commit to and follow through the maths
that would apply to a partition of a
universe into internal external and the
intervening blanket states that i repeat
can themselves be divided into active
and sensory states then you just get the
free energy principle and all that says
is it looks as if any
system
that is equipped with a markov blanket
and has to be in order to define the
thing in question
will appear
to infer
in virtue of the dynamics of its
internal states the external states to
put that more concretely
there it will be an interpretation
of the physical internal states
as encoding the parameters
of beliefs phasing beliefs about
external states and by parameters we're
just talking about these
location parameters and shape parameters
that
parametrize or describe any belief so
that's quite remarkable
because it gives you a very different
kind of
take on information
because normally when people talk about
sort of information theoretic treatments
or probabilistic treatments um
in self-organization on equilibrium
steady state so treatments um that allow
for this openness or exchange between
the inside and the outside through the
markov blanket and they're talking about
the information inherent in any
particular state you know how surprising
would it be to see this gas in this
ensemble in this configuration what
we're talking about here is something
much more subtle and it's a kind of
information that is much closer to a
folk psychological or a lay notion of
information it's information about
things that can't be seen
so the internal states now hold amazing
beliefs about
hidden external states that are hidden
from them because of the markov blanket
that defines their existence so there's
an existential imperative here
or one can read this existential
imperative
as
this inference process which brings us
back to self-evidencing that just to
exist as a thing
defi means that you have a markov
blanket which means that there are
hidden states which means that if you
exist and persist you must be in some
kind of technically generalized
synchrony
with the external states that means that
i can read off your internal states and
infer that you can as the thing
the configuration of external states and
this process in a dynamical setting
now becomes a process of belief updating
becomes a an inference process that can
be described technically
as
minimizing
a path interval um
of a
in physics called an action which is a
time times energy um
construct um as from hamilton's
principle at least action in our
instance the action is
the um
the the
marginal likelihood of the sensory
states
part of the markov blanket um which is
um
approximated by or may in some instances
be identical to the free energy so hence
the free energy principle is just a
principle of least action it's saying
that the internal states of anything
that exists
will have a description in terms of
minimizing
uh technically a functional of beliefs
about external states
so that was
a very brief
so so let me let me try and let me try
and summarize here if i if i can get
this so what you're saying is that
so
all biological self organizing systems
they are
ergotic they have the markov blankets
they exhibit active inference and their
self for self preservation or to put in
another way
all of the quantities
in a self-organizing system
that can change will change to minimize
free energy do i have this right yep
okay
so how
so i want to i want to go to this idea
of hidden states right so you obviously
talked about equilibrium
and i think maybe i would determine in
my world with something like homeostasis
right you know people in psychology or
people that do physiology they like to
talk about homeostasis
so maybe you can chat a little bit more
about the role of homeostasis or
equilibrium in preferred versus expected
uh various physical states
i
do want to introduce a little bit
because i know we've mentioned them a
few times you know mark solms i know you
guys have worked together i've talked to
him he's fabulous
um so he has a
psychoanalytic
angle here which i'm very fond of as
well
about
the impact of the freudian model of of
drive energy so maybe this is i'm adding
something here so maybe you want to talk
about homeostasis but my question about
freud is how does his conception of
drives or drive energy how is that
consistent with your free energy
principle
right
two really easy questions
right so you want to go from bernard to
freud
um
so but that was you know that that was i
think a clever move to to introduce the
notion of homeostasis so what we're
talking about here is just a generalized
homeostasis so you know um you can
regard um this
non-equilibrium steady state you use the
word ergodic which was interesting um
we try not to use that word because that
brings all sorts of baggage
what we're implying um in terms of a
non-equilibrium steady state is over a
limited period of time realizing that of
course at a slower time scale things
will evolve so
we don't imply that the system ever
attains a steady state it's just that it
has a steady state solution to its
dynamics but that solution may disappear
after a short period of time but within
a particular time scale
um what we are talking about is um the
the
fact that it has um
maintained
its markov blanket
which means that it must have
established some kind of synchrony or
balance between the inside and the
outside that we can now articulate as a
principle of least action or a principle
of least free energy or maximum model
evidence
and then the question is well is this
consistent with other theories and other
accounts of self-organization or global
function of a system and the answer is
yes absolutely and so
your homeostasis is one of my favorite
accounts but there are other accounts
you can also say well this um
fundamental objective function that
appears to be minimized remember this is
a principle of least action it looks as
though the system it looks as if the
system is trying to minimize something
so that could be a cost function which
could be a negative reward function or
utility function so you can now spin off
all of reinforcement learning
and economics in terms of utility theory
as one expression
with a particular commitment to you know
understanding the mechanics and the you
know the rhetoric of that field either
in the economics or psychology sciences
um but it's just really an expression of
that there is something to be optimized
or it looks as if the system is
optimizing something because it conforms
to this principle of least action where
action is the
negative log evidence of the free energy
so
all of reinforcement learning and
utility theory is just a statement i
think i can describe the behavior of
this
system as an optimization process what i
need to do is to identify the function
that's been optimized
and of course from our perspective
that's going to be or minimized in our
in our context that will be
a free energy
or
it's converse the marginal likelihood
and the evidence of my model the world
so you can rewrite all of reinforcement
learning and utility theory as basically
an expression
of or an optimization process of
self-evidencing
where you now start to interpret the
prior beliefs
and
as um or the logarithm of the prime
beliefs as a reward functional
preferences so just because um i am
sitting in this configuration with my
markov blanket uh means that
uh
the if i now interpret my behavior
in terms of basic mechanics i
necessarily now have to understand it or
write it down in terms of a
prior belief and a posterior belief in
the updating and it turns out that that
prior belief just is
the distribution of the um the
steady state solution that we were
talking about previously which means
that just existing is a statement of
your preferred states of being
and you can articulate that
mathematically in many different ways so
you know for example
in the theory of random dynamical
systems
the
um the set to which you will always
return will be uh called a pullback
attractor or a global random dynamical
attractor
these are just the states which i'm
attracted these are my preferred states
and because that's what's been optimized
from the point of view of reinforcement
learning or utility theory
you can move them to the observation
that the
the negative of these utility functions
or value functions is surprise that's
also known as self-information
information theory
it's just the prediction error we were
talking about before we try to minimize
that and then from that you can read up
all sorts of information theoretic
treatments of
optimal behavior such as maximum mutual
information theory infomax theory
you could even go as far to a certain
extent as integrated information theory
if you wanted to but information theory
accounts that posit some um
some
metrics some functional information
theory measure that is uh extremized of
course the free energy principle is just
one of these it says the information
theoretic measure is just the free
energy which is a bound on the negative
log
model evidence so marginal likelihood
but then you come to your set of
examples which would be um more from the
point of view of theories of
self-organization
either of a sort of physical sort like
cybernetics
and then you get into things like the
good regulator theorem and um
uh or synergetics which are entirely
consistent with this sort of
optimizations of your hamiltonian
principle at least action um but if
you're a physiologist all you're saying
is just hemistasis
this is just a generalized home mistake
it's um
trying to place bounds upon or it looks
as if you are we're in minimizing your
prediction errors
if you now think of a particular kind of
prediction error as the prediction error
between
any autonomic physiological variable
and your a priori set point or belief
about what it should be
in minimizing the prediction error you
are doing homeostasis so minimizing that
surprise in the particular setting
of the
surprise being about physiological
states just is homeostasis and if you
just generalize that you're all you're
doing when you're describing a particle
that keeps its states within particular
bowels within its mark of blanket it
necessarily has to resist random
fluctuations and gather itself up
to convince a generalized uh generalized
homeostasis
and then the final interpretation of
course is just in terms of
self-evidencing and the bayesian brain
hypothesis but these are just different
perspectives on the same underlying
underlying dynamic so having established
the the privacy of uh homeostasis in its
uh full and generalized sense we just
have to put freud
into the story which is not that
difficult actually um
and i say that because
i should acknowledge that mark zones
is the world expert on freud and you
know i don't know if he spoke about his
books on on
all the translations uh so my
understanding is childish and
unscholarly to say the least but from
what i understand having spoken to
people like mark
many of freud's um foundational ideas
were
coincident or shortly post stated much
of the work of helmholtz
so when when
what one might easily imagine that freud
thinking about sort of um
his energy constructs um
um
in terms of uh you know a freudian
construct
he probably had in mind the same kind of
thing that helmholtz had in mind and one
i hadn't seen anything written or i
haven't read about this but certainly
from secondary and tertiary sources
and the helmholtz did have a a notion of
a neuronal
free energy or a neuronal energy
that was the thing that could
be
optimized or minimized in order to
explain unconscious inference he never
really articulated or found it um but he
certainly had the quest in mind that i
fondly or would now submit would be the
variation free energy it fills
everything that he wanted and is
entirely consistent you know with his
more formal um formulations of of
perception and also much of physics um
so my guess is that the basically freud
was was um
taking that notion of um an optimization
in terms of uh
an energy function
as it was articulated and conceived of
at the time that these are the inception
of these ideas that you're bringing
canteen philosophy into physics
but without the machinery afforded by
richard feynman to deal with it with
your in in a simple and graceful way in
terms of mathematical equations uh and
without of course the uh
you know high performance computing that
machine learning subsequently enjoyed
was able to demonstrate proof of
principle that you know this is the way
to format the problem so you know
fry probably got as far as he could in
the absence of fiberinesque maths and
pathogen formulations and big computers
but pursuing these kind the same kinds
of ideas so it needs of no surprise to
me when mark tells me that there is a
a
fundamental consilience between freudian
formulations and those that you would
find that inherit from uh feynman and
you know and all the other
contributors to these you know to this
formulation of sense making um so
i i would imagine that freud gets into
the game quite gracefully um
you know the particular point i think
that mark zones would emphasize here
though brings us back to
this um this metacognition and beliefs
about beliefs and in particular
um
the
the ability of certain
hierarchically abstracted sophisticated
particles like you and me
to actually physically encode
and manipulate
uh and do their bayesian leaf updating
on beliefs about beliefs and
specifically the precision the
uncertainty to know our own uncertainty
to know our own minds
and the deployment of that in terms of
this
overarching homeostasis this
extremization of
minimization of prediction error or free
energy or maximization of marginal
likelihood or moral evidence and
underwrites that kind of mental action
and may on mark's view at least um be
the essential quality
of any um any fur any feeling or any
sentience so he has a lovely phrase
called felt uncertainty
you know
in the same way that we um visually
palpate the work that you know the
visual scene with our eyes
and what he's suggesting well the the
way that i interpret his his his poetry
and he may be very cross if he hears
this but the way i the way i interpret
it
is that you can palpate your your own
uncertainty palpate you can feel your
own precision
and furthermore you know and have prior
beliefs about the way that that
uncertainty should be deployed or
changed and you update your beliefs
about that precision and the mechanisms
that do that um may well be
um those that are at the heart of
um
the feelings under right quality of
experience of the kind that the mark
would ascribe to you know to
consciousness
felt uncertainty
yeah it's it's interesting with freud
because obviously a lot of it in terms
of the the
the drives was this um
uh i'll say is it it was a
in an interesting way i mean the way he
framed it was
in terms of the psychological hierarchy
that he was trying to give as a model
was this element of tension reduction
rooted in our
our biological and evolutionary nature
if you were to make a comparative
analysis here you would say that that
was probably a passive approach right
because it's always something is
happening how do we how do we resist how
do we how do we get rid of the tension
reduction
is it in a way it kind of pass away as
opposed to maybe say the you know
philosophy of frederick nietzsche who
had a more active way of trying to
understand energy and drives and power
and things of that nature
okay so some of the further questions i
want to ask you are since we've
done a a very nice or you've done a very
nice job of of explaining the the free
energy principle
um
i would i want to ask about how it
applies
and then a little bit of some criticism
so i guess the one connection here
is about consciousness so as we've been
alluding to people many people have
ideas about
consciousness where
resides
how it functions
so everyone from um chalmers to dimasio
to obviously mark has has made some
pretty um extraordinary
uh research on this in terms of finding
it in the uh
[Music]
in the mid brain the brain stem which is
fascinating stuff there
um and all and now seth i mean there's a
bunch of people that have been talking
about consciousness it's sort of trendy
how do you
based on everything we've discussed um
bayesian brain
free energy principle how do how do we
can this tell us anything about
consciousness more
accurately or more clearly about what it
could be where it could be
how it functions um what is i guess your
your kind of a stamp on on this topic in
terms of
consciousness
i think the first thing to say um which
is often said by philosophers is that
the free energy principle is not a
theory of consciousness
that sounds um
slightly deflationary but in fact it's
quite a useful thing because if it's not
it wasn't designed to explain
consciousness and um
certainly people like me have no
pretensions to try and get into that
game but it will be very interesting to
see if it holds
the
um
the formalism that allows people to
address certain hypotheses or questions
about consciousness so that that is
deeply engaging and just for your
interest um
there's currently just been funded a um
john templeton foundation
collaborative adversarial collaboration
to play off uh active inference against
information uh integrated information
theory so there are lots of academics
and theoreticians out there who are sort
of um
interested in
what more formal accounts of sentient
behavior will bring to the table in
terms of answering questions about
consciousness um so everything i am um
saying is contextualized by the fact
that you know
the french principle is not there to
explain consciousness
if you had to
answer some of the deeper or more
challenging questions um
such as um
david chalmers hard question
um
and or accommodate um
some fundamental dialectics you know
cartesian dualism for example
what space is on offer um from the free
energy principle and i think there are
some quite clear answers there and we
can take this from a number of
directions um i'm gonna
i'll take two because they follow on
from from um
some of your uh pressing questions about
sort of drives you know from the
freudian perspective um so what what did
what would drives look like um from the
point of view of
the free energy principle but let's not
talk about the free energy but let's
talk about active inference as an actual
process theory for you and me um
that um
that are if you like uh conforming to
the free energy principle and so
the the first thing that um
one has to note
is something we've spoken about before
that we have a calculus
four
beliefs about something
that immediately introduces um a duality
in terms of interpreting internal brain
states
we can either talk about the
problem probabilistic population
dynamics and the information
of
populations on their activity
which would be
um uh
intrinsic to the brain you know how
likely is it that my neurons are going
to fire in with this particular pattern
of this particular part of the brain in
this particular circumstance which of
course is your one of the key questions
that we address with your imaging
or
you can under the free energy principle
or active imprints say well hang on a
second there's another kind of
probability structure a belief space
because we've just said
for every
pattern of neural activity
there is encoded an implicit
representation of beliefs about the
outside
now what that means is technically
that not only is there um a
probabilistic description of my neural
activity but that neural activity is
equipped with something called a
statistical manifold
by by which i simply mean that every
point
on this manifold that corresponds to a
pattern of brain activity
is equipped with
a belief
structure a belief distribution a
bayesian belief
about something else about the outside
about you the causes of my sensations
and that means that
i can now talk about an information
geometry
of a different sort which is now about
the outside and extrinsic information
geometry and that's quite a nice picture
because
this notion of belief updating we've
been talking about phase in belief
updating
um
is
corresponds to a movement
on the statistical manifold so you
imagine that every pattern of activity
in your brain corresponds to a point on
this abstract manifold this
surface is a very high dimensional space
and every time the pattern of activity
changes
in virtue of your neural dynamics you
make a movement on that space and that
movement is belief updating it is
exactly the same as moving from the
prior to the posterior that we were
talking about before
so sensations come in and they move
the
point on the cystical manifold to
produce the belief updating so you are
literally now
describing mathematically in with an
information geometry belief updating and
the process of imprints
and
the the key link here
is that the
the measures the
the metrics that define this information
geometry of belief updating
um
something called fisher information
metrics and mathematically
they correspond exactly to the precision
we were talking about before
so technically it's the curvature of
that space as measured
by the uncertainty or the precision of
your belief updating so there's an
intimate relationship now
between the
precision
that we were talking about in relation
to
um say mark zones and just to slip in
here that the cells of origin
of those neurotransmitter systems that
control the post-synaptic game that
mediate the precision are exactly in the
mid-brain structures that mark thinks is
the seat of consciousness so this is all
entirely internally consistent
but it's also consistent with the
fourier notions of drives because you
can think about this movement on the
statistical manifold
this belief updating has been driven by
forces
what are these forces they are the
prediction errors they are the
um the surprises
they are the effect of the likelihood on
the
priors that force it or move it to
produce the posteriors so now we have
this notion very elemental notion of um
a drive
um
probably
sort of oversimplified from a freudian
perspective but i think the mechanics so
holds true here that the drive is
literally the thing
the the uh role of the prediction errors
in driving belief updating from prior to
posterior police but crucially we now
understand this force this drive as
being gated or nuanced or contextualized
by the precision which brings us again
back to the
fundamental importance of getting some
sort of metacognitive beliefs about
beliefs or predictions of uh of
precision right in terms of
enabling those particular forces and
drives to be
manifest in the way that we both
organize our neural activity but also um
uh explore our belief space by moving
around on the statistical manifold so
you can write this down very precisely
in terms of information geometry there's
lots of really interesting maths that
gets right into
the world of gauge theories and the like
all telling the same story that the the
the potency of these drives depends upon
the curvature and the curvature depends
upon the precision or our our beliefs
about the uncertainty
the point here though from uh from the
sort of consciousness point of view
is that there are two descriptions of
movement on this statistical manifold
there's a description from the
extrinsic perspective in terms of the
probability distributions encoded by a
point on the manifold and there's
another intrinsic description which is a
simpler one just about the probability
of being having this pattern of your
activity so there are people that are
thinking uh
about uh colleagues such as uh
vanilla vice
who
together have um put this forward
as a way of repairing dualism you've
basically got a dialectic for free
mathematically in the information
geometry
that
jointly ascribes
a
particular physical instantiation in
terms of neuronal activity and patterns
of neural uh neural firing
to any point on the statistical manifold
that is accompanied by beliefs about
something else which would be the sort
of the more mindful aspect of a
cartesian divide so you've got this sort
of um
a molistic
account that has these dual aspects of
mindful belief updating and the physical
embodiment of that um
i think it would be a
potentially useful way to talk about
sort of dualism versus versus uh
modernism when it comes to you know
some some
possibilities to be historic but to my
um limited understanding sort of uh you
know foundational issues in uh
in consciousness research
and that that that would be that would
be sort of um
one um if you like opportunity for
um
the the bayesian mechanics
afforded by active inference and the
free energy principle
to
produce some quite clear predictions um
about the relationship between mindful
stuff and brainful stuff um where there
has to be if you like a convergence
within this
within this information geometry the
other thing it brings to the table
is that
it is the movement on this manifold it
is moving through a belief space
that is the essence of inference so if
you remember the free energy principle
is just trying to describe the dynamics
of
a system that has a non-equilibrium
steady state solution for a certain
amount of time
inherent in the use of the word dynamics
is you're looking at a process that is
unfolding in time
what that tells you is that if you want
to talk about consciousness
then it may be best to think of
consciousness as this process of
uh of belief updating
in exactly the same spirit that we talk
about evolution as an evolutionary
process
we don't talk about the state of
evolution at any particular time that's
divorced from the dynamics the paths
and the process itself the the process
of evolutionary selection um as opposed
to say selecting a plan or a particular
belief or a pro you know um
you know are updating my beliefs in
terms of the process of uh inference
under the basic brain hypothesis
you know we talk about the process as
unfolding in time
so what that would mean if you just
translate
that perspective which is inherently
dynamical
to consciousness research is that
questions about what it is to be
consciousness have to be recast in terms
of what processes must you convince in
order to qualify as
having a conscious process so states of
consciousness and levels of
consciousness are
um only meaningful when they apply to
something that is changing in time
essentially moving on this on the
statistical manifold so that's uh from
my point of view a couple of things that
are brought to the table
by having a formal mechanics or calculus
underneath belief updating to have a
calculus of sentience a physics of
sentience that tells you immediately
you're talking about processes and of
course if you think of you know in terms
of
any optimization or casting things in
terms of any optimization
um then you are talking about the
process of optimization and indeed even
um from the point of view of the
the the semantics of things like
variational principles and least action
you know the least the minimizations
aspect of it talks again to a process
that is you know playing out over time
so that that would certainly be um
if you like
one's constraint on author for anybody
who talks about consciousness you know
are they committed to a way of thinking
about consciousness that just doesn't
have any um
any meaning
in the sense that it's it's about a
particular state of being
um or can they recast or formulate their
hypothesis in terms of uh of of a
process
the third level um or the third sort of
um thing on offer
um with active imprints
brings us back again to the generative
model so remember previously we were
talking about differences between uh
thermostats flies mice and men
and
i was very comfortable talking about
those differences
uh from a unique perspective which was
simply what are the differences in the
generative models so if you can boil
everything down to the
evidence
for which you are trying to secure which
is the generative model then you can
start to talk about different kinds of
consciousness in a graded way
in terms of different kinds of genitive
models and we've already had this
conversation in the sense that you know
i can have a genetic model for a
thermostat which has um which is
temporarily very thin it has just you
know very very limited temporal horizon
and then we graduate to
particles and creatures that have a more
allostatic as opposed to a homeostatic
um way of engaging actively with their
environment that require certain
temporal depth and then we move on to
um the the opportunities
when you now have a charity model in the
future for different outcomes different
counterfactuals and then we move into
anil seth's notion of counterfactual
richness but noting the counterfactual
richness
as one way of understanding
consciousness or conscious process
can own is only allowable
when your charity model
has a
uh the capacity to model counter factual
outcomes in the future
um and then we get to um the remarkable
counterfactual it comes under write
things like this you know the
philosophical zombie and braided of that
and then we start to talk about you know
we can go from mice to men to
philosophers and then start to engage uh
engage with that kind of conversation so
that's another you know sort of
structural architectural
formal
um
thing uh or um
way of dealing with these questions that
you get from the physics and the
mathematics which wouldn't otherwise be
there if you're just using narrative
arguments
historical arguments
i was going to say you were talking
about this convergence and as you were
describing that i was thinking about how
there is a kind of multi-dimensionality
or a continuum aspect of this having a
being a process of things as opposed to
just this static
kind of state which i think
based on many of the things i've read on
consciousness that makes a lot of
intuitive sense and i think the way that
you're talking about this underlying
calculus to try and describe
a kind of process makes a lot of sense
in terms of
artificial intelligence so maybe we can
make the
the leap a little even further right
mice to men to philosophers to ai
right how do obviously there's there's
it's sort of connected with the
consciousness question although you
could make artificial intelligence that
doesn't need to be conscious um i don't
think it's a prerequisite although some
people may argue about this but in terms
of again
the this underlying calculus that is
there with the free energy principle
what
what is it i guess specifically or
um
something that gives it this uniqueness
that can
give us information about
artificial intelligence
obviously artificial intelligence is a
very broad
categorization so i mean my you know
dishwasher and microwave is a form of
artificial intelligence right at a very
very low level um and then there's
artificial intelligence that we see in
science fiction uh stories uh such as
you know humanoid robots that are
sentient and they maybe have feelings
and you know things like that over time
so there's a whole gamut here and of
course you could make the the offshoot
of well first you have to define
intelligence which is a
very long
footnote which we don't have to do
although if you want to i would totally
be fine with you explain that as well
but just how do we understand the
elements of free energy principle for
artificial intelligence now and how it
could have potential utility as we
continue to grow and expand our
mechanics or computational aspects of
artificial intelligence
part of your question was you know how
how
does a free energy principle
give you the opportunity to get more
information about the uh the nature of
intelligence and as you uh integrate
sort of artificial intelligence um
interestingly that that
that getting information about is
actually at the heart of the answer i'm
going to give you so the answer i'm
going to give you
um
i'm going to foreground though um one
key thing which is um
in response to a previous question here
what's the free energy principle for um
very much like the theory of natural
selection it doesn't really do anything
afraid because it's it's it's very
pretty and you can have philosophical
debates about it which i'm sure we'll
come to um but you know
why is it useful
and the answer is um
if you read the free energy principle as
a
mechanics
that is apt to describe
systems that have solutions to their
non-equilibrium steady states in terms
of an inference process
then
the answer is it's pretty you know it is
not useful
however once you know the functional
form of the equations of motion the
dynamics the updating
that have to be in play in order for the
system to be intelligent or to be to
show a self-maintaining or
autopoetic-like behavior what you can do
is
write into an artifact the generative
model and all the prior preferences
entailed by that genitive model to
simulate an artifact that has the same
properties of itself maintaining and
maintaining its markov
blanket
why would you want to do that well i
think there are two cardinal reasons why
you might want to do that why would you
like to build
a markov blanket maintaining building
machine that's doing inference that it
basically is
realizing
the
principle at least action that
prescribes the differential equations
that you would write into a computer
simulation or indeed a a robot or a you
know
an artifact that was supposedly showing
artificial intelligence well i think
there are two reasons to do that
one you might want to build
an active inference agent an artifact
that's actually doing active inference
how would that differ from artificial
intelligence as we currently know it
that's a really good question there are
very clear answers and i'll and i'll
give you those answers in a second but
just to
conclude this part of the answer uh with
the second motivation that you might
want to build
synthetic
agents with synthetic sentience
under the variational principle of least
action that is the free energy principle
is you might want to
make inferences about somebody else and
i know now thinking from the point of
view the psychiatrist you might now want
to try and simulate choice behavior and
active inference
under a particular model and then adjust
the preferences and the price of that
general model until you reproduce the
kind of observable behaviors that this
patient has or this particular cohort
shows so what we're talking about here
is essentially
using
the
simulation models as observation models
of real world people you know and other
creatures
in order to try and understand their
internal dynamics and their internal
mechanics
there's something quite fundamental um
about that particular take because
remember before
we we talked about the markov blanket in
shrouding the internal states of
something from the external states so
that there is if you like an
impenetrability there's a fundamental
statistical divorce between um the
internal states and the external states
meaning that the external states are
hidden from the internal states but the
converse is also true
which means that from the outside the
internal states of any creature or
person or loved one
are forever hidden from you from the
outside so you can only ever infer
the machinations and the dynamics and
the belief updating on the inside which
is interesting because that means you
know
much of my day job in your imaging is
trying to peek behind the markov blanket
to see what's going on but you you can't
do it properly your otherwise you'd have
to break you'd have to reach the markov
blanket to become invasive or study dead
things in order to
try and infer what was going on so that
means that you need to
you need to use inference just to
understand the internal dynamics of the
brain of a person which means that the
only way you can do it is to have a
genetic model of a genetic model which
means that now you've got another use
case for active influence in the free
energy principle which is building
models of people and patients and then
adjusting them until you use the
adjusted model that renders the um
the behavior of the model
um very similar to the behavior of the
patient to infer this is how the patient
works or at least this is as if you know
and as if explanation are counted as
patient so
those are my two principal motivations
you know
to use these as
a principled model of choice behavior on
your rural responses that i can measure
empirically to answer my hypotheses
about how the brain works
there is another agenda which we've
touched upon which is you know
more the fun of creating artificial
general intelligence of general
general intelligence or agi
and the distinction between artificial
intelligence and
agi or the next wave of um you know
artificially
or intelligent artifacts um i
personally do think um is staring you in
the face um um
in terms of what
the difference is between active
inference um
under more sophisticated genitive models
that have
the ability to
model the consequences of action
so
if
the end point of this argument
is that
if it is the case
that i
have to minimize my prediction errors or
free energy or at least look as if i am
minimizing my prediction errors or free
energy just to exist if it is an
existential imperative
for existence
then a priori i must also believe that
every action that i choose every choice
that i make
must be that which is the most likely to
minimize prediction errors or free
energy
after i've made that action
the consequences of my action are now
scored in terms of their ability to
reduce
the free energy i expect following an
action
so then what you can do mathematically
is look at the expected free energy
and ask how could i interpret that what
does it look like what are the qualities
how what are the first principle
accounts of a good choice or a good
action
and when one does that um
it looks like as you might expect um
there are a number of different
interpretations of this expected free
energy which is a big thing that active
influence brings to the table so this is
an objective function that now
replaces utility functions and
reinforcement learning
it also replaces the um
the
principles that underlie active learning
and things like
optimal bayesian design in the sense
that it grandfathers these things and
puts both of those two aspects of good
behavior um together
and in putting them together
this objective function that underwrites
the right choices
the right behaviors
is just
expected surprise or uncertainty which
means that
all i need to do is to choose those
behaviors that minimize or resolve
uncertainty or maximize information gain
under prior preferences inherent in my
generative model so that last statement
is quite crucial and what what it
transpires um to be also the expected
free energy transpires to be a mixture
of
two components one of which is
an epistemic information
hungary seeking component and the other
one is a more pragmatic preference
seeking component and put them together
they are just then minimizing overall
uncertainty or minimizing the expected
expected free energy
crucially the epistemic information
component
is the the thing that underwrites
curiosity
so if you look at the artificial
curiosity literature they um
the the key problem is
has been
how do you
um articulate and mathematically
formalize the drives to resolve
curiosity the sensation seeking the
inquisitiveness that characterizes all
the you know all of us certainly in
certainly in the context of this
conversation but uh you know i think all
of us as as little scientists i just
need to live
we have to be curious creatures
and the expected free energy is
basically that curiosity that intrinsic
motivation that's another word in your
in
neural robotics developmental
neurobiotics
also known as expected salience
and it puts it together with the
surprise minimizing aspects endowed by
having prior preferences in your gender
model i i expect myself to do this kind
of thing or
encounter these kinds of outcomes but uh
because i'm um
contextualizing that with this
information curiosity
seeking
component i've now got a complete
objective function that essentially
equips active inference agents with
curiosity so that is what is missing
in ai that no
um
alexa or no
iphone
is ever going to ask you a question
because it's curious about you
so the next generation of artificial
intelligence
if it complies with the you know the
variational principles of least action
as articulated under active inference
should show a genuine interest in you
because it will act or it will select
those questions and those actions or
look at these websites or these
data
engage in this kind of data mining
simply to resolve uncertainty about its
generative model of the world and if
instead of model of the world um
contains you it'll want to know about
you and it will ask the best kinds of
questions that will maximally resolve
its uncertainty about you so it'll be
genuinely interested in you
um and you know
in that sense then i think because it's
got this um
curiosity
inherent in its
selection of its actions i think it will
then show
a kind of artificial intelligence that
is much closer to the generalized
artificial intelligence that people have
been been aspiring to but it does rest
upon this upon putting the curiosity in
as part of the package by minimizing the
expected free energy
i i have this this chilling a fantasy in
my mind as you're telling me this about
you know my my uh alexa or my my siri on
my phone asking me questions about just
a very very chilling kind of thing about
it but i do agree with you i do think
that that's probably the
uh
the next step the next place because of
how good algorithms are at trying to
predict based on things that we're
searching or looking or things like that
you know it's trying to to to to
accurately get something if i put a
search in google now it takes you know
not even two seconds right you know 10
years ago it took longer and you have to
find all these things it's trying to
curate the things for you that you're
searching
i could imagine that there's more of a
not just that the the ai is is receptive
but then expressive in what they're
trying to ask and inquire of you the the
person that's searching which is
uh there's a little bit more you're
right there's like a
more of a two-way street there which is
um
definitely uh
it's a little bit of a scary thought to
think about i think there could be
really cool utilities to it but i
definitely think there's obviously like
many things in inherent danger
before i want to ask you about the
imaging techniques you've done because
that's i mean as you say your day job is
is uh
that's what you do and obviously you've
been
prolific in those those areas i just
want to ask one thing just because it's
relevant now and i think as we
um
continue uh moving throughout
this you know second uh decade i guess
of the 21st century um
it's about your work with
copen19
and i know this is a big big area big
topic and
a lot of noise about
the pandemic in
all aspects i just want to ask you just
generally you can briefly just summarize
you know kind of how what what your work
was i believe was with uncertainty and
predictive models and how we understand
things and how we understand um
certain types of immunity and things
like that just kind of how you became
involved or how you how you think about
uh
about you know the the pandemic and and
covet and how
um
how you've been doing work in in that
area
yes of course so um
the answer to that question does come
from my day job
which
is using
brain imaging and empirical
data acquired through a variety of
different ways of peeking or breaching
the mark of blanket or looking inside
people's heads so you can do that with
things like
functional magnetic resonance imaging
which gives you sort of whole brain
images every second or so in
reports fluctuations in
coarse-grained neural activity in
different parts of the brain right
through to
things like magnetoencephalography
and
equivalent eeg procedures which give you
a much temporary resolved picture or
signals reporting electromagnetic
fluctuations in your activity over
your fractions of a millisecond
but the price paid is that you you lose
the spatial resolution but
the point being is that these are
ways of looking at the brain in action
and um affording
data empirical evidence for various
hypotheses about the underlying
functional brain architectures of which
we have been talking a lot so the
hierarchical architectures the recurrent
message passing entailed by different
say predictive coding or other theories
and in particular um something from my
perspective um
trying to understand the
failures of those architectures in terms
of false inference uh that ensues from
for example breaking the precision
control that we've been talking about
and how that might show up in people for
example with schizophrenia or depression
or other neurological or psychiatric
conditions so that that's my day job and
the
link to the covered research
is quite um
easy to uh
demonstrate in the sense that
what you are talking about when looking
at a message passing architecture and
your role or message passing
architecture that is doing the belief
updating that is um enacting the drives
afforded by prediction errors in doing
the belief updating and causing activity
in different parts of the brain
this obviously can also be
expressed as
a communication and a dissemination of
information or influences so you've got
the spread of messages
um bits of information from one neural
population to another neural population
in order to make sense of the brain
imaging data you actually have to have
an underlying genetic model of this
process and now we're talking about a
genetic model of the brain and i as a
scientist are using to make sense of my
scientific or empirical data that comes
from the brain imaging and and i've
deliberately phrased the
um
the fundamentals of these generative
models in terms of
spreading information
among neural populations because of
course that is exactly the same kind of
genetic model you'd use when trying to
model the spread of a virus amongst the
populations that constitute a country or
a region or a city so my involvement um
in the um
the modeling
of the coronavirus epidemic
comes straight from the
observation that the
generative models the state-space models
the convolution models these are just
technical terms and the kinds of models
we
use to make sense of brain imaging time
series generated by populations of
neurons could be very quickly and
efficiently repurposed to make sense of
the epidemiological time series
generated by populations of people that
were in various states of infection
symptomatic
you know vaccination and the like so for
the past two years
my
weekend job has now been split behind
between
um
something called
bayesian model selection or structure
learning which is basically fiddling
with your geometric model until it
minimizes its free energy or maximizes
its marginal likelihood in relation to
the uh the data that's
incrementally becomes available and
different kinds of data um on the one
hand and then trying to do the um the
free energy principle and make it
simpler and more and
more accessible on the on the other hand
so that's how i became involved
you know different levels of engagement
um
working um as a panelist on the
independent stage which was a sort of
um
a public facing version was meant to be
a compliment
a public-facing complement to the uh the
scientific advisory group on emergencies
that were supplying the cabinet office
and the government
with advice we were much more
in its original formulation sort of
public service facing information um uh
dissemination and public engagement sort
of um
initiative uh run by academics um
i have been involved
on other advisory bodies um largely
motivated or
resting upon
the
um the predictions made by um what's
called dynamic causal modeling of the
time series data that allows you to
optimize
the parameters of that generative model
given all the data you have up until
this point in time
and then run the model forward
under you sometimes in different
scenarios that allows you to make sort
of forecasts about what would happen if
i did this or did that it can be useful
for
um nuancing the advice given to to your
politicians and
decision makers when considering you
know should we
relax lockdown rules at this point
should we
encourage this age group to take up
vaccines for example
yeah no that's that's super super
salient and instrumental so that's
that's uh that's incredible work
um so we've already kind of talked about
it so let's let's get into your day job
your your with the imaging techniques um
so
the thing that i think is your initial
claim to fame here is the statistical
parametric mapping and then i think also
subsequently the voxel-based
morphometry these are the two imaging
techniques most people will know a ct
scan an mri scan
i do want to ask you about fmris some
people may know about diffusion tensor
imaging there's all different types of
ways of scanning the brain
uh so maybe just tell us what these two
things are the statistical parametric
mapper and the voxels and then just kind
of how that sits in with a mapping of
the brain uh uh overall
right well you introduce the notion of a
ct scan and then many people will also
be familiar with x-rays your images um
that peep behind the curve and get on
you know give you a picture of what's
going on on the inside um so statistical
parametric mapping
can be conceived of as producing x-rays
of significance of significant
activation and by activation i mean a
change
so going back to this notion that the
interesting stuff is in the processes
the uh
from the point of view of the free
energy principle the belief updating so
you needed a way of forming
x-rays
of a certain kind
that reported
where the belief updating and the neural
activity and the hemodynamic or the
blood flow consequences of that human
dynamic activity where and when they
were occurring um in the brain so spm or
cystical parametric mapping is just that
it's just it's just the construction of
x-rays or ct scans
where the values of the image at any
point in the image usually known as a
pixel or a voxel correspond to a
statistic testing a particular
hypothesis about the pattern of the um
the fluctuations in your activity over
which you have usually some experimental
control so when people talk about
activations what they basically mean is
has there been uh have i been able to
evoke
neuronal or belief updating and neural
message passing and thereby neural
activity and everything that supports
that neural activity
by presenting this kind of stimulus to
the subject relative to that kind of
stimulus so you're just comparing the
evoked responses over time and then
summarizing those differences in terms
of a statistic and then putting that
statistic for that part of the brain
into an image and thereby creating a
whole brain map or a you know
statistical x-ray of the functional
anatomy so it's now unlike a ct scan
which is a structural anatomy this is
not the functional anatomy because
you're you're
if you're like summarizing a functional
process and very similar approaches um
you are taken to um
in eeg or electromagnetic
and electrophysiological um procedures
you mentioned voxel-based morphology
that is simply the application of
this
statistical x-ray this spm like
technology
to the special case of
sequences of um structural images
so you're normally in the game of trying
to infer
to this group of patients say with
alzheimer's disease or parkinson's
disease do they show a systematic
difference in their structural anatomy
again in this instance using a an spm or
a statistical x-ray but in this instance
the statistic is reporting the
significance of the difference in the
composition of the anatomy as measured
with um with magnetic resonance imaging
usually or could be ct scans um
by uh but using here not time series
data but usually data points from
multiple subjects that can
carefully uh carefully selected
so it sounds like there's a there's a
there's an integration of trying to have
the integration of looking at the
functional pieces and time of a process
for a structural picture
is is what it sounds like it's trying to
do how you use this for schizophrenia
um particularly how did you
use these methods to understand more
um
schizophrenia and how literally the
images of the brain for for individuals
with schizophrenia how it looks and how
it functions and maybe just talk about
that as well i'll just as a as a as a
footnote
um
i worked in patient uh with individual
and outpatient but in-patient with
individuals that have schizophrenia so i
i've uh i've been around these folks for
a
good part of my career and um they're
they're very very fascinating um
individuals
in terms of personality in terms of
their cognition in terms of their brain
functioning and you know being on plenty
of uh
you know treatment plans and big big big
long meetings with psychiatrists and
neuroscientists uh trying to understand
um
schizophrenia but then also understand
and how to try to provide clinical
services to individuals with
schizophrenia so i'm curious as well
personally almost of of
how how did you use these these
techniques to try and understand
specifically uh individuals with
schizophrenia
right again that's an excellent question
and it speaks to the motivation for much
of the theory of the work that we've
been talking about so understanding
um what has gone wrong in certain people
um qualifying this of course the you
know
so the schizophrenia would not like you
to think that their brains have gone
wrong
that's right that's right
right they just have a different reality
that's all exactly um
i felt that's mathematically true by the
complete class there but that's another
story um
so
so um
the way that all this fits together is
um
in terms of um
[Music]
understanding
much of psychiatry and
many neurological syndromes in terms of
false inference
and if you can understand the
experiences
of a psychiatric patient in terms of
false inference then now we already have
a mechanics
that is what we've been talking about
active inference and free energy
principle and predictive coding basing
brain
we already have a mechanics at hand to
ask at what point
has there been some aberrant um
message passing or belief updating that
could lead to this uh this false
inference so you may be asking well
why on earth would you want to cast all
of psychiatry is false inference
well it's a very natural way of
accommodating that that's where the
symptoms lie that's where the ontology
of psychiatry lies it's in belief
updating it's in beliefs about the world
so when i talk about false inference i i
mean it in a you know in a simple sense
of type one and type two errors false
positives and false negatives
so when you think about say a
hallucination what is that well it's
just inferring something is there when
it's not it's just a title on a kind of
false inference
what about neglect syndromes agnosia
dissociative syndromes um they are
just false inferences of the second kind
if something is not there when it is
uh and i think you know if you think
about it nearly all psychiatric
conditions can be construed in this way
either falsely unfair something is there
when it's not and vice versa
so what that means is you you now move
on to the
uh the more challenging and pragmatic
questions well what could account for
this
kind of um
false inference and the questions then
can be um either to
the structure of the implicit generative
model that that is in tamed uh so
entailed
by
our brains or the
the process theories that undergird the
message passing and the physiology of
that message passing
and what you're basically
talking about is a form of disconnection
now this disconnection may sound odd to
talk you know immediately about
disconnection but remember the
architecture of any distributed system
is defined by its connectivity the very
notion of a hierarchy yeah depends upon
the absence of certain connections that
would otherwise transcend levels in say
a linear subsumption hierarchy so
connections are everything in terms of
sculpting and defining
the architectures
that
endow the brain with an implicit
generative model of you know its lived
world
um and furthermore the message passing
that
you know enacts the drives the belief
updates um you know the precision
weighted prediction as we've been
talking about and those are just
expressions of influences from one
part of the brain to the other part of
the brain so it's all about the
connectivity
and that means that you need to now um
use the empirical data
in a way that enables you to answer
questions about disconnections
and they can come in many flavors you as
a neurologist
you know subscribing to uh early ideas
of um disconnections from people like
gashwind um in terms of lesions
to
the organs of connection in the brain
the white matter tracks that connect the
other long range fibers that connect
different parts of the brain these can
be sort of macroscopic
disconnections
from the point of view of schizophrenia
research that that idea
was first proposed by wernicke who was
famous for you know his studies of
specialization functional specialization
in the language system but his big gift
uh in terms of psychiatry was was the
junction hypothesis that you could
understand
dementia precocks are early formulations
of schizophrenia in terms of disruption
to these uh the organs of connectivity
the white matter tracks that we
currently um that we currently study
with things like um
diffusion uh weighted
resonance imaging or diffus
tractorgraphy then
based upon that uh that kind of imaging
but there was another perspective which
most people ascribed to boiler um which
spoke more about the sort of the
fine-grained disintegration of the
psyche the the
loss of coherence and um
um
you know literally you're a dissolution
uh at the level of mental life so from
our perspective that would be belief
updating
which
one might nowadays understand much more
as a microscopic disconnection the level
of synapses the little
specializations little buttons that or
plugs that connect one neuron to another
neuron at the end of the
the axon or the long fibers that emanate
from a particular neuronal cell there's
a a
whole bunch of pre and post-synaptic
specializations called you know called
synapses which you basically in the
little plugs at which all the
neurotransmitters act
um so
in um
clinical neuroscience you know a failure
of or a disconnection or a failure of uh
integration at the synaptic level will
be known as a synaptopathy a pathology
of synaptic connections so that's the
kind of disconnection that most people
have now in mind when thinking about the
abnormal message passing that might um
produce the false inferences
characteristic of different psychiatric
conditions
that means you need to be able to
measure this you need to have an in vivo
in life way of measuring the synaptic
efficacy the connection strength the
gain that we were talking about before
that is modulated through the precision
engineered
message passing getting the excitability
right these are all different ways of
expressing the synaptic efficacy the
strength of connections in the brain and
if you think that
things like schizophrenia
are manifestations of false inferences
that inherit from a very pernicious and
particular kind of psychopathy
precludes getting the precision right
getting the excitability of say for
example neurons reporting prediction
errors correct
then you need to be able to measure it
and that's where
the third technical um
contribution to brain imaging comes in
which is the dynamic cause of modeling
that that was used to study the the
pandemic so we use the the the the
dynamic causal modeling
to basically um study the spread of
viruses from person to person um but it
was originally devised to study the
synaptic efficacies that underwrite the
spread of signals from one member of a
neuronal population to another one so
that's where it's at at the moment i
mean
it's difficult for me to um
really
summarize you know what we were doing
and what we are doing um in a nutshell
because a bit like the your your first
questions about how much we
i have achieved in my career i think
this field also it's a long journey and
it's very incremental and sometimes
you're quite surprised by how far you've
moved but if you look about
the progress from this year to last year
it's almost zero you have to look over
20 years
from my perspective at least
dynamic cause of modeling that was that
was explicitly um
done in order to understand
disconnections and sign up topics in
schizophrenia because that's where you
know that's where i came from in
psychiatry um then
it's about now that people are starting
to take this technology seriously and
start to apply it um at scale
and in a way that is
underwritten by
companion studies of the same systems
and different models in cell cultures
for example so you know there are
if you've got one generative model under
the hood that explains
disconnection of a certain kind due to
this synaptopathy which we're now
associating with abnormal precision
control of exactly the same kind that
mark was intimating when he's talking
about his broken midbrains because these
are the ones that
broadcast the signals that control the
synaptic efficacy
um
uh you're in exactly the same way as you
might imagine that happening in
parkinson's disease where you've got
abnormal um you're a hypodopenergic
state
the complement in schizophrenia being a
high potentially hyper dopamerging state
and many other conditions um
so those that that application of
dynamic causal modelling at different
scales and across scales is now starting
to emerge at least in proposal form um
no one yet has had the nerve to fund it
my hope is in the next year or two there
are sufficient number
there are a sufficient number of proof
of principle
that it now becomes uh you know a viable
um
uh way of proceeding and
just
to bring things to closure
the two areas that
seem to that have really exploited
this
um way of making sense of data to get at
synaptopathies are
epilepsy research in particular
childhood epilepsy and some
neurodegenerative conditions so that
that's where the action is at the moment
yeah i could definitely see that
um i want to ask just just as a since
this is your kind of more closely you're
closer to this is about fmris um just as
a small
side here many people were very excited
about fmris when they came out you know
this is very
um
literally colorful
and
exciting in some ways but
over time i guess over 30 years now i
mean there are some people that would
say that it's a kind of you know modern
day phrenology
right
do you agree with that what's the
utility of fmris if anything and
you know how good is it really at
translating into i guess better
treatments you know because you know
some area because we know with diffusion
tensor imaging that there's all of the
brain is connected all of it is linked
up all of it is is is talking with each
other different parts of the brain
cortical subcortical different lobes
everything's talking to each other
so
how do we understand i guess the utility
of fmri's if at all um
and and how how could it translate i
guess into to better treatments
so you um saying some people are
starting to call it a sort of
latter day uh phrenology if
they were calling it that at the
inception
[Laughter]
the new cartography the new the neon
phenomenon right um which is a fair a
fair critique um
so i think the the answer to that
question is a little bit like
this you know how far we've come in our
journey
if you ask year by year yes the the
advances have been incremental at best
but if you just look back um with
a temper resolution of decades
fmri has had
quite
a profound
impact on the clinical cognitive and
translational neurosciences so
simple things which people of your
gentle and tender age will
not be aware of
simple things
that you take for granted
were just hypotheses in
1989 1990
for example the whole notion
of functional specialization in the
brain that underwrote sort of fedorian
modalities and and all sorts of
hypotheses about um in fact
also
subtended neophrenology the notion that
one part of the brain did this and
another part of the brain did that so
this is a notion of functional
specialization in particular segregation
that this particular functionality was
segregated anatomically or spatially to
this part of the brain uh and that
therefore we had at least a good
hypothesis about the
um
predictions that would ensue foreign
brain damage and we can make some
guesses about the importance of
connectivity under the functional
segregation hypothesis no one knew
though
no one
up until 1990
you know 1989
knew what no one knew that um there was
for example um color specialization
in this particular part of v4
um that was segregated in the sense that
there was no color related responses
elsewhere
you couldn't do that because you'd have
to have electrodes everywhere in the
brain
in order to show that it was this part
of the brain responding to color and not
that part of the brain so it was only in
in the early 1990s that people could
actually after about 200 years possibly
150 years um confirm the original
hypothesis about functional localization
specialization and segregation in the
brain that was a profound thing as i say
from your perspective you you know you
just assume that people in the 1980s
believe that functional specialization
was the principle of brain organization
they did believe it but it was just a
hypothesis
and there was doubt after fmri there was
no doubt it was just part of the
foundation of neophenology
the second sort of big point to make is
that you know if you want to understand
how a virus spreads um or how a meme
spreads or how um messages spread in a
deep neural network or how belief
updating operates in a functionally
segregated specialized hierarchical
brain
you have to have
a way of identifying the things that are
connected so if you are truly a
cartographer when you go to a new
country the first thing you do is
identify the landmarks before you start
worrying about the communication the
rivers or indeed if it's a
a developed uh country the roots of
communication the rail links and all of
that good stuff the first thing you do
is have to identify what's happening
where in terms of these functionally
segregated um uh definitive aspects of
any map or before you can talk about
distributed pressing well distributed
about amongst what well amongst the
functionally specialized areas where are
they
we can now identify those using fmri
but of course that's just the first step
so within about sort of five to eight
years people were turning their
attention to the real question which is
back to the connectivity it's about it's
back to the principles that underwrite
the distributed presence saying as you
say understanding why every part of the
basis could be connected at least with
two degrees of freedom to every other
part of the brain so that that's where
the big questions were and um
subsequently addressed in terms of
fundamental distinctions between things
like functional effective connectivity
um
there was um
you know a period when all the
excitement was about some measuring
correlations and and functional
connectivities in the brain um but uh
throughout that period of course you
know
things like dynamic cause and modeling
were being developed in order to measure
the actual uh directed coupling that
subtended these correlations that people
measuring with functional connectivity
so
was fmri or is fmri useful in that
regard and has it had any material
effect on um
sort of treatment i i i mean i can cite
particular examples in terms of
epileptic research and identification of
sort of
eloquent areas the use of
imaging as a biomarkers in uh say
genetic studies of predisposition to
various illnesses you know i could give
you a number of some um so quite
compelling but very um colloquial
examples of where it has worked i would
i would sort of concur with you though
there hasn't been an awakening of
insights it's more a consolidation of
what we have known from centuries of
careful neurological and neurophysiology
an ever-increasing fine-grainedness that
allows us now to talk about the
particular subreceptors involved in a
particular syndrome that underwrite the
synaptic or the autopathy that's
producing the the disconnection in your
in this particular system so the
interceptive system involving the
anterior cigar
and the anterior insula so it's really
people really drilling down on the fine
grain in certain quarters of your energy
there's a lot of be great stuff as well
um but you know the a grade uh
mechanistically uh mechanistic um
um
theory-driven applications
hypothesis-driven applications of
neuroenergy you know really has advanced
quite quite remarkably on in the basic
neurosciences that you know whether that
has yet to translate into um clinical
neuroscience you know i think that's an
open question but you know
the answer i think will only reveal
itself when you look back and say what's
happening the past 10 years
and you probably get a much more
positive
response than otherwise just one final
comment and it certainly is the case
that fmri
as
um
an imaging modality
has lost its shine
in the sense of its appalling temporal
resolution
um which means that most earnest imaging
neuroscientists
are or cognitive neuroscientists or
indeed clinical neuroscientists
would want to supplement the
the cartographic
gift of fmri
with highly resolved electromagnetic
electrophysiological responses so you
know anybody doing any serious imaging
neuroscience nowadays would
also recourse to electromagnetic signals
and standing distributed processing at
that level guided by
the cartography on offer from fmri
yeah no that's that's that's important
to to to also
uh uh keep in mind as well
well my my
my last question for you
is uh
i guess sort of a sort of a big one
uh there's two parts to it
so the first part is
you've talked about many of your
um theoretical uh principles you've
talked about some of the stuff from the
the imaging techniques
so we've talked about the bayesian brain
which has some utility or has many
utilities but many people are are
starting to talk more about it
mainstream and have been for for many
years but in terms of your free energy
principle and how you use this with
active interference inference excuse me
predictive coding theory
how
how do how
do you think
this can be
translated to the common person right
how can people
use
these wonderful
uh theoretical structures
and frameworks in a way that's applied
and has some pragmatic utility and ways
that everyone can kind of grasp and say
oh yes
i got that and i see how this is really
important or use it in various uh uh
clinical practices in whichever domain
in psychiatry neuroscience and
psychology et cetera
how how do you think um
the ability to translate those models
and theories into practical applied use
is is is key and and and ways to do that
and then
larger frame or larger or of this is
for neuroscience as a whole you know how
do you see i mean neuroscience you know
its utilities maybe some of its
limitations but how it's it's useful for
for people to continue to understand the
complexities of neuroscience
in a sense we've already
sort of covered i think the the two key
um practical applications
um and
perhaps it would probably just to
rehearse the point that there's a lot of
similarity between the free energy
principle and
the theory of natural selection you know
in and of themselves they do nothing for
you you've actually got to want to
answer a question in a particular
situation or to build something um
um
you know in a given circumstance um and
then the other free energy principle and
its attendant process there is will
certainly provide you the functional
forms and the architecture the mechanics
to do that quite quickly and efficiently
um so the question now is why would you
ever want to build those things and how
could you practically use them um so in
terms of um building sentient artifacts
you what you know
i just
remind um myself and you know recall an
early part of the conversation that what
we have now is a
an off-the-shelf set of belief updating
schemes
that should in principle um create
curious sentient robots and artifacts
that will be um to my mind the next step
in artificial or machine learning
and i say that from a number of
perspectives first of all in terms of
you know what's um
what what is a use case that would be
appreciated by
members of the public i i generally
think that it's probably going to be the
manufacture of little pets
as much
of sort of you know public facing ai
has pursued
but the difference will be here
these artificial pets will actually have
a curiosity
and it will be some it will be much
easier to um project and
anthropomorphize
and to
apply theory of mind to these kinds of
little curious pets and so they'll
become increasingly um
more like your actual favorite uh pet or
your your or your dog
simply because they now have um
curiosity under the hood
so that's how i personally think people
are going to make money out of active
inferences just equipping these little
robots
with a bit of curiosity
or to use jurgen schmidt he was phrasing
artificial curiosity um and
interestingly mentioning yogurt of
course he you know he thinks that's the
essence of creativity and fun it's this
is curiosity this epistemic drive this
information seeking part of resolving
uncertainty or maximizing information
again through actively uh soliciting
evidence for your generative models of
the world
in terms of machine learning
and the more
i think pressing
a less trivial issue of
sustainability
the whole point of active inference is
that it is
a bayes optimal in the way that it gets
data and assimilates those data and that
optimality expresses itself in
certain kinds of efficiency
which i think are going to be very
important in terms of sustainable
computation and energy use so i've heard
that in 2025
about 20 percent if not 22
of
the total energy consumption globally
will be um
by data farms and uh you know e-commerce
and exchange so this is
a really if you like
thermodynamically and climate change
relevant observation
there are good ways to make imprints and
to data mine and there are bad ways
now the good ways are those that conform
to hamilton's principle at least action
that's the free energy principle that
you minimize in your process of
inference or active inference you
maximize the evidence which
mathematically simply means minimizing
the complexity
with
under accuracy constraints where the
complexity is the
the cost you pay in terms of belief
updating is literally
that measure of movement from the prior
to the post area
that costs energy via the zheninski
equality which means if you use the
wrong kind of overly parametrized
generative model
say with a billion parameters in a
state-of-the-art learning network
you are doing it in the
statistically least optimal way and
using a massive amount of electricity
so another way of stating that is the
direction of travel in machine learning
in particular deep learning
is exactly the wrong direction because
it relies upon big data an overly
parameterized overly complex charitable
models
so i'm hoping that active inference in
the free energy principle will reverse
that direction of travel through proof
of principle so what we have instead now
is not throwing
billions of data points
at your deep learning machine and
millions of dollars to a team of um
engineers who are trying to
handcraft and tune the parameters of the
of their particular variational auto
encoder along short-term memory
layers in you know a convolutional
network
instead you will spend you will
let the machine itself decide what is
the most informative data it needs to
resolve its uncertainty it will run
either
on an edge computing device but it's
only running your laptop and it should
finish and converge within minutes to
days as opposed to days to months and it
will cost you a hundred dollars or even
ten dollars as opposed to up to a
million dollars so
i'm
deliberately completely overstating
the benefits but
you know
that reversal or direction of travel um
is mathematically um
uh uh
obvious it hits you in the face when you
start to sort of articulate computation
and
intelligence in terms of the process of
inference and just look at the
underlying maths in terms of the
information geometry and then using
things like the jinski equality to
understand that in terms of the both the
computational cost but also the
thermodynamic cost of computation so i
think that's going to be
in principle i'm sure i'm completely
wrong i'm probably talking complete
rubbish but in my little fantasy world
data mining is a thing of the past you
won't need data farms because instead of
going for mining big data
these curious machines will go in mind
just the sparse data they need to
resolve their uncertainty for what they
are um
for the context in which they operate so
we'll see a move to edge computing with
sparse data
but it will be bayes optimal in the
sense it's just returning to the basic
principles of optimal basic design
established in the 1950s by people like
david lindley sort of
revisited by people like david mackay in
terms of active learning in the 1990s
and then apparently completely forgotten
about uh until the active inference
movement or push back against the
direction of travel and
sort of standard deep
learning approaches or even
reinforcement learning without the
curiosity
it's it's it's it's incredible to think
about all of the avenues that it that it
that this has the potential to to expand
uh with well
i mean i i don't know what to say uh
carl you've been so
so generous uh i mean more than generous
with with your time and i i consider it
a great privilege and honor that you
have given me over three hours of your
time to explain this that's that's quite
the gift and i greatly appreciate that
is there any final comments that you
want to say or anything that you want to
summarize or anything like that and and
then also
i'm very impressed with the old staliner
stamina and also there's some you know
the patience with which you ask your
questions
wait for about 20 minutes for for
example of an answer that that is quite
remarkable so thank you
no i the the pleasure is is all mine you
have been very very generous and i i am
quite sure that listeners will be uh
very very thrilled to to hear all of
your wonderful
work that you've been doing so um can't
say enough thanks appreciate it
[Music]
you